<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>English paradise Discouered in the Latine prospect of Iacobs blessing. Preached at S. Buttolphs without Aldersgate at London, on the holy Sabboth commonly called Trinitie Sunday, in that ioifull season of the festiuall solemnities for the blessed creation of the most gracious Prince of Wales.</title>
            <author>White, John, 1570-1615.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14985</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119683</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854890</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854890</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20345</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14985)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20345)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1016:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>English paradise Discouered in the Latine prospect of Iacobs blessing. Preached at S. Buttolphs without Aldersgate at London, on the holy Sabboth commonly called Trinitie Sunday, in that ioifull season of the festiuall solemnities for the blessed creation of the most gracious Prince of Wales.</title>
                  <author>White, John, 1570-1615.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 61, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Hall for Richard Redmer, and are to be sold at the Starre at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Ih. Wh., i.e. John White.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20345:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Engliſh Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>DISCOVERED in the Latine proſpect of IACOBS Bleſsing.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GEN. 27.27.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Ecce odor filij mei ſicut odor agri à domino benedicti.</p>
            </q>
            <p>PREACHED AT S. BVTTOLPHS <hi>without</hi> Alderſgate <hi>at</hi> London, <hi>on the holy Sabboth</hi> commonly called <hi>Trinitie Sunday,</hi> in that ioifull ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the feſtiuall ſolemnities for the bleſſed creation of the moſt gracious <hi>Prince</hi> of WALES.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by WILLIAM HALL for <hi>Richard Redmer,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Starre at the weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20345:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20345:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Knight Sir <hi>John Holliſe,</hi> Comptroller <hi>to the Prince his highneſſe houſe-hold,</hi> proſperitie with aeternitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, it is long ſince you did firſt looke on mee with your helpfull fauour. I haue for twentie yeeres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe times ſtood below in the common place of the Church: yet ſometimes I haue beene drawne vp aboue the obſcure ſhades of the Countrie, and by forceable intreaty, riſen higher then is ordinary for ſuch an heauy lumpe of refuſe mettall.<note place="margin">Piſtillo retu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius.</note> And being in London at a feſtiuall triumph, I was a partner of the common ioy for the ioyfull proſperity of our moſt hopefull Prince of Walles. Then and there I was preſſed forth <hi>(aere amicabili)</hi> with a friendly motion, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an actor in that great aſſembly. I muſt confeſſe. I was willing on my way, which made my labour more light, ſo that I hallowed that holy Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath with two Sermons, as a paire of Pigeons, or two yong Turtles.<note place="margin">Luk. 2.24.</note> I did wiſh richer offerings to beſtow in ſuch a ſolemne ſacrifice of Vowes, but I brought my beſt, to teſtifie for my heart. What though I am vnworthy of reſpect, as the leaſt Bell in the Temple <hi>(imo ne tintinnabuli in fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bria veſtimenti Araonici)</hi> not worth a little Bell vpon the skirt of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> Ephod.<note place="margin">Exo. 28.33.34</note> Yet I thought it my duty without any intreaty to ring my Bells that day in the holy place. When I had comfortably ended my daies worke, it came to paſſe beyond my thoughts, that one of my auditors and I exchanged thoughts. He as it ſeemed a francke Popeling, of his chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty offered me his thought, that I was too officious. I for a preſent reward beſtowed my thought on him, that I was excuſable, as the man which being requeſted to goe a mile with his friend would goe twaine.<note place="margin">Matth. 5.41</note> I was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be warned and to take better heede to double diligence, <hi>abundans
<pb facs="tcp:20345:3"/>cautela non notet.</hi> Heere I reſolued neuer to perach vp to the preſſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the learned ſages and holy writers:<note place="margin">Vitiligatores tantum exti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſcens.</note> therefore did I ſeriouſly reſiſt all louing importunities intiſing mee to venture looſe coppies of this and other my weake labours into the hands of my chiefe friends.</p>
            <p>My reaſon for my deniall was, <hi>quia neſcit vox miſſa reuerti:</hi> a man may ſhoot foorth two arrowes with more eaſe and ſpeede, then fetch one backe againe. Yet now at the length I haue yeelded my ſelfe, and preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſend my firſt fruit to my firſt friend liuing, in your acceptance to liue or dy. I muſt confeſſe my deſire is that you would accept it as a wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come preſent of my humble thanks (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) and thinke my thanks as hearty as I meant them. You haue heard the cauſe wherefore I ſtayed theſe twins at home ſo long after their birth, with a centurie of their naked brothers.<note place="margin">Agrippo ſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or.</note> I doe willingly acknowledge mine owne pouerty, by which I thought my ſelfe vnable to cloth them with decent apparel. And I was ielous of their rude education, leaſt I ſhould heare worſe of them abroad then at home. If I haue beene too ſlow, I craue pardon with my feare to be too haſtie.<note place="margin">Ne incalciatus in montes.</note> Let it be ſaid of me, that I am too like to many of <hi>Adams</hi> kindred and mine owne: that I haue learned more good rules then I can obſerue, as that of <hi>Columella: Matura ſatio ſaepe decipit, ſera ſemper mala eſt.</hi> Yet I reſt in hope of your loue which I haue chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie loued. I might adde ſome expert extenuation of this ſeruice which ſpark of Art may better become my betters. <hi>Namque ſi Scotiſta Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricetur,</hi> he is eaſily eſpied, <hi>vt Graculus inter muſas.</hi> It is inough for me in this illuſtrous age of high Science, and rich Art, <hi>Craeſi pecuniae te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runcium addere.</hi> Therefore to preuent many needleſſe words, in theſe few I yeeld my ſelfe to owe ſo much vnto you, that I muſt remaine your debtor for euer, and</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>yours</hi> Ih. Wh.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20345:3"/>
            <head>ENGLISH PARA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DISE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GEN. 17.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold, the ſmell of my ſonne is as the ſmell of a field, which the Lord hath bleſſed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be, that ſome among you, doe no more need a Seer, to ſhew you the myſteries of this Text, then Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles want ſpies for the ſpace of their flight:<note place="margin">Job. 39.32.</note> 
               <hi>Their eies behold afarre off.</hi> Yet I muſt make bold to tell you, that which ſome of you can ſcarce beleeue: That this Text is Paradiſe. And it is more likely ſo, becauſe the head of it is <hi>Ecce,</hi> and Chriſt is <hi>Ecce,</hi> the head of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, of the Church, <hi>as the husband is the wiues head.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtus eſt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delium domicilium aeternale, vt Paradiſus erat innocentum tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le.</hi> The riuers of this Paradiſe, are theſe foure; <hi>Odor, Filius, Ager, Benedictus,</hi> all iſſuing out of <hi>Ecce;</hi> as thoſe foure riuers which did run out of the head fountaine of Eden. And out of Eden went a riuer to water the garden; and from thence it was diuided, and became into foure heads. Chriſt is <hi>Ecce,</hi> the head fountaine of Eden, <hi>propter emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentiam, continentiam, influentiam,</hi> for beautie, plentie, and bountie: a fountaine opened to the houſe of <hi>Dauid, Zach.</hi> 13.1. The riches of Paradiſe are excellent, for in the floods of one riuer is Gold, &amp; Bdeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, and the Onix ſtone. In the Gold is truth, glorie, and incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:<note place="margin">Gen. 2.12.</note> in Bdelium, mercie, ſweetneſſe, and medicine: and in the Onix, faith, aduantage for the ſight of the eies, the glaſſe of the ſoule.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Come forth ye daughters of Sion, and behold king Salomon with the Ecce. He ſhall giue you drinke out of the riuer of his pleaſures.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 36.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Ecce</hi> of my Text, <hi>Mercie and truth are met together,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 85.10.</note> 
               <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20345:4"/>and peace haue kiſſed each other:</hi> all holy ſtreames of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. Holy ſtreames indeed, for euery one of them is a riuer of this Garden,<note place="margin">Numb. 20.11.</note> running out from <hi>Ecce,</hi> for the reliefe of thirſtie ſoules, as the waters which guſhed out of the rocke abundantly.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Odor</hi> is mercie, all ſweet ſmell of mercie, life to the Church, life in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ludolphus. <hi>Pſal. 141.2.</hi> Vt apes praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>què flores quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritant, ita ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias dei. Caietan. Arbor ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens &amp; reſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens vt mortui reſurgant or reſumpti vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant in aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. <hi>Ioh. 14.6. 1. Cor. 1.20. Pſal. 42.12.</hi>
               </note> in whom all our praiers are as incenſe, and the lifting vp of our hands, as the euening ſacrifice, all ſweet.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Filius</hi> is truth, the word of eternall life, and ſtandeth here, in the middeſt of this little garden, dropping dewes of heauen to water it; as the tree of life in the middeſt of Paradiſe. <hi>In caeteris erat alimentum, in iſto etiam Sacramentum:</hi> By other trees the body had ſuſtenance, by this the Soule inſtruction. Therefore was it called, <hi>Arbor vita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum:</hi> Chriſt is the tree of liues. <hi>Behold the tree of life in the middeſt of the garden, on whom the liues of all the Saints doe depend for euer. Chriſt is the truth, and the life of the Church, all ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Ager,</hi> is righteouſneſſe: O inualuable righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, where we gather all our righteouſneſſe: for <hi>Chriſt is made vnto vs righteouſneſſe. Iſte eſt regula, nos regulati:</hi> He is our guide, and we his followers, as liues are guided by their ſoule. Thus are wee made to flouriſh like the <hi>Palme tree, and to growe like the Cedars of Lybanus, all faire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Benedictus</hi> is peace, our healthfull peace in our deere peace of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, our redeemer, whence wee receiue our heauenly requiem, and reſt from all our labours, all bleſſed.</p>
            <p>Thus we receiue our lot of inheritance,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 1.12. <hi>S. Caſſianus.</hi> Ioh. 20.</note> among the Saints in light, <hi>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem ſocialem cum angelis in vinculo pacis,</hi> The legacie of the Prince of peace. <hi>Irrequietu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt cor noſtrum, O bone Ieſu donec quieſcat in te:</hi> O ſweet Ieſus, how our hearts doe pant till they reſt in thy peace, that we neuer pant any more. Here you may perceiue a comely Quadrant of the Soueraigne <hi>Ecce,</hi> like that beautiful type of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whoſe borders were foure ſquare.<note place="margin">3 Reg. 7.31.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Church is alſo reſembled by the <hi>Quadras:</hi> a pretious ſtone foure ſquare,<note place="margin">S. Ambroſe.</note> of deſpected colour, yet of reſpected vertue. <hi>Quadratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſignificat ſtabilitatem Eccleſiae:</hi> the quadrant imports ſound reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. But it is likely that ſome will aske, where is <hi>Dominus,</hi> the great Maſter of the houſhold, he which is Lord of the ſmell, the Son, the Shield, and the bleſſing: In whom, by whom, for whom, &amp; from whom, mercie, and truth, and righteouſneſſe, and peace, <hi>and all things are.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11.36.</note> (In all things, let me vnderſtand what I ſay, and tell you what I do vnderſtand:<note place="margin">S. Auguſtine.</note> 
               <hi>Omnes vtique naturas intelligere debemus quae naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20345:4"/>ſunt, neque enim ab ipſo ſunt peccata quae naturam non ſeruant ſed vitiant:</hi> Wee muſt meane all natures which are pure iſſues in natures for from him are not any faults which doe not conforme nature, but deforme it.) Now then, to that queſtion I anſwer, that I cannot ſhew him, when hee goeth by one, I ſee him not.<note place="margin">Iob. 9.11.</note> If I goe to the North where he worketh, yet I cannot ſee him:<note place="margin">Iob. 23.9.</note> he will hide himſelfe in the South, and I cannot behold him. <hi>Enoch</hi> is ſaid to walke with God, but he was taken vp into the Eagles ned, and no more ſeene:<note place="margin">Gen. 5.24. 4. Reg. 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>Elias</hi> went to walke with God, but he was rapt vp in fierie chariots, and no more ſeene here, till the transfiguration for a fit. Man here cannot ſee ſo farre, as to ſee what God is. Therefore <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he was on the lower Mount, did hide his face at this <hi>excellens obiectum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3.6.</note> which doth dazell mans preſumptuous intelligence, more then the Sunne doth his piercing eie: the Sunne is a creature, God is the Creator, <hi>finitiad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some ſay, that <hi>Iſaias</hi> was therefore ſlaine,<note place="margin">S. Hierome.</note> for ſaying that he did ſee God; yet (without peraduenture) he did ſee him, <hi>iuxta poſſibilitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manam, non vti eſt, ſed vt voluit ſe videri:</hi> ſo farre as man could ſee, who cannot ſee God, as his deſire is to ſee, but as Gods pleaſure is to be ſeene.</p>
            <p>You may remember, when the Lord was asked for his name, his anſwer was, <hi>I am:</hi> wonderfull and paſt vnderſtanding.<note place="margin">Exod. 3.</note> Wee grant in good meaning, that there is <hi>meridiana viſio,</hi> when we ſhall ſee face to face, when we ſhall know that wholly,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.12.</note> which wee know now but in part. But that <hi>meridian</hi> ſight cannot ſee God fully, to comprehend or meaſure him: <hi>Deus ad plenum non cognoſcitur in via, neque in patria:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſichius.</note> The ſharpeſt ſight, either at home, or abroad, cannot diſcerne the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God. We ſhall know him to the full,<note place="margin">S. Augustine.</note> for the ſufficiencie of our felicitie, which ſhal be perfect, and to the capacity of our glorified con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, which ſhall be great, but not infinite, as God is: and ſo is nothing elſe. <hi>When I awake I ſhall be ſatisfied with thy Image.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 17.15.</note> Many millions of painefull conſiderations haue beene inrolled in the monuments of the Church, of the Secrets of God; which are all, but as all the nations,<note place="margin">Eſa. 40.15. <hi>Alcuinus.</hi>
               </note> as the droppe of a bucket in compariſon, or as a droppe to the Ocean. Some haue deſired to tell vs what God is of himſelfe, and what hee is to vs. That of himſelfe he is all length, <hi>id eſt,</hi> eternitie; all breadth,<note place="margin">De us eſt Sphae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis, cuius cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum eſt vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia nuſqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> charitie; all height, maieſtie, all depth, wiſdome. That he is to vs, our poſſeſſor, he abideth within vs, and is not contained; our guard, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth without vs, and is not debarred; our king, hee continueth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue vs, and is not mooued; our rocke, he ſupporteth vs for euer and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20345:5"/>is not confined. I might point out vnto you, many gloſſes of faire ſhew, and all ſhort of that which the Apoſtle in few wordes attempteth to this purpoſe.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>He onely hath immortalitie, and dwelleth in the light which none can attaine vnto, whom neuer man ſaw, neither can ſee.</hi> Yet in all our walke through this garden, wee ſhall ſee his beames ſhining vpon it, and with faith, hope, and loue, admire his preſence, whoſe ſeat is in the pillar of the cloud.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 24.</note> Now then let vs proceed to conſider, firſt, the head of this Text, with the antecedents; and then the foure quarters, with their correſpondence.</p>
            <p>In euery part we find three conſutes.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Firſt, hiſtoricall narration pleaſant, in <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 Secondly, myſtical ſignification ſplendent, in Chriſt.</item>
               <item>3 Thirdly, congruent application honourable, in the Prince.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In the head, <hi>Behold,</hi> I muſt craue fauour to walke a long proceſſion.</p>
            <p>The Lord had promiſed a bleſſing to <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the number and honour of his iſſues: count the ſtarres, if thou canſt; ſo ſhall thy ſeed be: numberleſſe as ſtarres for exceeding plentie, glorious as ſtarres for heauenly beautie. This promiſe was ſure, yet it came on with leaden feete; <hi>Abraham</hi> was long without a child, and <hi>Abraham</hi> was longer without the child of Promiſe:<note place="margin">Artopaus.</note> 
               <hi>quanta maiora, tanta longius protracta Dei beneficia, vt ſint chariora vt Iſaac, Chriſtus &amp; vita aeterna;</hi> The greateſt bleſſings ſeeme many times a great way off, that we may more deſire them, and bid them better welcome. At the length, that <hi>Ecce,</hi> and wonder of the world was borne (for none of the Lords words ſhall fall to the ground) one liuing fruit of two dead ſtockes;<note place="margin">1. Sam. 3.19.</note> his father an hundred,<note place="margin">Gen. 17 19.</note> and his mother ninetie yeares old. Aske his name, it was <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac,</hi> all laughter;<note place="margin">Gen. 21.6.</note> well may he laugh which winnes, well did he winne, which did winne Chriſt, in whom all the nations of the earth are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>Iſaac praeludium Chriſti de quo fideles rident,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Guil. Lugdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ex quo omnia Dei dona in fidelibus rident: Iſaac</hi> was Chriſt his prologue, for whom all true hearts haue pleaſant thoughts, and all faire gifts of God in his Saints, are through him very delectable. But yet the bleſſing reſteth, <hi>ad aras,</hi> as if God had euery day a conſultation with himſelfe for the progreſſe of this bleſſing. <hi>Iſaac</hi> was not directed to his wife, till hee was fourtie yeares olde,<note place="margin">Gen. 25.20</note> and <hi>Rebecca</hi> was barren till twentie yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. What is Gods promiſe come vtterly to an end? no: all this ſtaie was the whetting of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, and the exerciſe of <hi>Iſaacks</hi> pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, longing for <hi>Ecce. Quamuis in Iſaac promiſſa eſſet ſucceſſio, tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> implenda erat precibus Dei praefinitio:</hi> Albeit the Lord had giuen aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of ſucceſſion in <hi>Iſaac,</hi> yet the performance was ſo ordained,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20345:5"/>by zealous petitions it ſhould be obtained. The praiers of them both in good time preuaile with God though ſorrow continue for a night,<note place="margin">Pſal. 30.</note> yet joy commeth in the morning, after praier. They and their aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants pray for a bleſſing, and the bleſſing falls double on the ground.<note place="margin">Cant. 7. Gen. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Rebecca's</hi> two ſonnes are like two yong Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>os that are twins; for <hi>Iſaacs</hi> wife conceiued, and ſhee bare two nations in her wombe. Shee for a while went weeping,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 1.8. Pſal. 126.</note> as <hi>Hannah</hi> did (albeit ſhee had an husband better then tenne ſonnes) and carried pretious ſeed, yet ſhee did returne with ioy, and brought her ſheaues double.<note place="margin">Vita humana plus aloes qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mellis habet. <hi>Gen. 26.</hi>
               </note> I ſhall not need to fill this <hi>Ecce</hi> with the various and periſous temptations, which came to <hi>Iſaac.</hi> If I might ſhew them all, you all might maruell that euer he could reach this <hi>Ecce.</hi> Let this one inſtance ſuffice, which was a lamentable di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtreſſe vpon him,<note place="margin">Wallenſis.</note> that hee had not ſo much as ſweet waters to nouriſh him: <hi>Fidelium profectus impij non ferunt aequanimiter:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auicetus.</note> The wicked pine away at the proſperitie of the godly. All his enemies labour vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſubuert him, and euery neighbour ſeemed to him an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note> labouring to ſubuert him, that he might be vtterly ruinated: but the Lord was his deliuerance, as he hath been ours in an oppreſsion much like, or worſe then this. For what portions of truth wee haue found in the word of truth, as wells of liuing waters, to nouriſh vs and our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the Popelings vitiate them.<note place="margin">De caudis vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes cognoſcas &amp; de fimbrijs texturas.</note> They either equiuocate vpon them (this their double dealings) or hide them by the ingruences of their multiplied <hi>Index expurgatorius</hi> (fal ſhood in fellowſhip) or ſtop them vp with gloſſes and earthly traditions (this their packe of knackes) leſt our Chruch ſhould thriue too faſt. But ſome will ſay, why ſay you ſo of the Papiſts, they are our neighbours? It is true, as the Philiſtims were neighbours to <hi>Iſaac:</hi> Enuied welleth at the next doore:<note place="margin">Quotvicinos habemuo toti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem hoſtes.</note> and a man doth often bring his worſt companion from home. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, our kinſmen are our in-bred vipers; as <hi>Parſons, &amp; eiuſdemfa rinae millenarij:</hi> and thouſands of the ſame vnpurged leuen.</p>
            <p>Here is the cauſe why wee haue ſo much a doe to keepe cleere wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the welles which our fathers haue digged:<note place="margin">Hi ſunt qui Eccleſiam in vagientem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguere &amp; adultam cona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſunt hare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tics. <hi>Gen. 26.15.</hi>
               </note> they for very ſpite haue filled with mudde, and ſtopped them vp with earth, which they haue digged out of their infernall pits to this purpoſe. Thus the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims had enuie at him, and filled vp with earth all the welles which his fathers ſeruants digged in his father <hi>Abrahams</hi> time. See then how vnlikely it is for vs to hold in the breath of diuine knowledge, as for <hi>Iſaac</hi> to abide in the ſpirit of life, if God were not with vs. <hi>Sed à Deo adiuti refodimus puteos paternos ab inuidis paleſtinis obturatos:</hi> but in the name of the Lord we diſcouered our fathers fountaines, which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20345:6"/>Philiſtinian enuie had hidden from vs. Thus the Lord was on <hi>Iſaacks</hi> ſide: <hi>Feare not Iſaac, for I am with thee, and will bleſſe thee, and will multiply thy ſeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then to goe on with <hi>Ecce,</hi> behold on thing more ſtrange: <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca's</hi> two children were at ſtrife in the mothers wombe, like the two Hebrewes at ſtrife in the field. <hi>Potuit eſſe naturalis cauſa, ſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſit myſtica &amp; ſupernaturalis:</hi> for that wonder, there be reaſons ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in nature, but there was a ſupernaturall reſpect aboue reaſon. The two younglings are both wreſtlers,<note place="margin">Hipolitus.</note> both wreſtling for a wonderfull prize, for a bleſsing, a birth-right, a crowne: O bleſſed crowne of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall glorie.<note place="margin">1. Pet 5.4. <hi>Rupertus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Collidebantur paruuli eodem Dei nutupermoti, quo ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationalia pecora &amp; inanimata elementa futurorum praeſagio permoueri ſolent:</hi> The tender younglings werre ſtirred to their conflict, by the ſame motion, in which we ſometimes ſee, both beaſts without reaſon, and elements without life to ſtirre, that their ſtirres might be Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of after-claps.<note place="margin">Luc. 21.</note> So ſhall there bee ſignes in the Sunne, and Moone, and Starres. Surely the guerdon was greater then the wreſtlers thought of, yet their thoughts ſeeme to contend for the prize, which the weaker winnes by grace. The Weezell doth raiſe his force againſt the Baſiliske for ſoueraigntie in that place where they meet, and ſhee being armed with Rue,<note place="margin">Succus rutae palet contra ſerpentes, vt gratia Dei <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ontra Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os. Rupertus. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Hierome. Septuagine. Symmachus.</note> preuaileth in the combate. Thus the younger ſapling <hi>Iaacob</hi> being armed with the hearbe of grace, <hi>vincit fratrem Baſiliſcum,</hi> he puts his brother to the foyle. The ſtrife is diuerſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the varietie of tranſlations: ſome, <hi>conquaſſare</hi> to ſhatter, <hi>ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruere</hi> to ruſh one on another: ſome, <hi>confringebantur, collidebantur,</hi> they did offer mutuall violence one to another: ſome, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>lude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant &amp; calcitrabant,</hi> they did kicke one the other: ſome, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudinem nauis in ſuperficie ferebantur,</hi> they ſeemed to ſwimme in their mothers bellie. But here a Schollers braines may ſwimme in ſuperficiall obſeruation to little purpoſe. Wee yeeld to that which wee reade with approoued iudgement: <hi>Fratrum diuortium portendit ebri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onum colliſio.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ucherius. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aietane.</note> 
               <hi>Sed non omnino eſt certus modus commotionis infantum:</hi> The mutuall violence breathing on thoſe tenderlings vnborne, did preſage their ſeparation after their birth.</p>
            <p>The good woman perceiuing a ſtrife in her wombe, as of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inmates in the Bee-hiue, ſhee went to aske the Lord for the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of that ſtrife;<note place="margin">Gen. 25.22.</note> 
               <hi>Seeing it is ſo, why am I thus?</hi> I may not trouble you with the bundles of opinions how ſhee was anſwered, or by whom. It is needleſſe to argue, whether it was <hi>Sem</hi> or <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> or they both at once; or it was <hi>Heber,</hi> or (as ſome thinke) it was <hi>Abraham,</hi> as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20345:6"/>it is moſt like, for circumſtance of time, place, and perſon. His perſon (aboue the reſt) was of neereſt acquaintance, of ſureſt faith, and euident grace of reuelation, for hee was a Prophet.<note place="margin">Gen. 20.7.</note> The opinion of the moſt learned is, that ſhee went to aske the Lord, in the Science of ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Patriarch, at that time as <hi>Abraham</hi> was. Whoſoeuer reſolued her, the Lord ſent her word by him what ſhould betide her, and the Church word by her, what ſhould befall the Church.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the rare bloſſomes of <hi>Ecce.</hi> Behold two manner of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall be diuided out of thy bowels, faithfull and vnfaithfull out of one ſtocke, pure and impure fruit of one tree, true worſhippers and heretickes in one Church, ſincere holy ſeruants, and prophane coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit obſeruants, as a grape and a brier-berrie both of one vine, a lambe and a woolfe both of one damme.<note place="margin">Beda.</note> 
               <hi>In Eccleſia ſunt ficus &amp; vna Chriſtus, tribulus &amp; ſpina Diabolus;</hi> In the Church are both figges and grapes, for Chriſt is both figges and grapes; and in the Church are both briers and thornes, for the deuill is both briers to catch, &amp; thorns to hurt.<note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> 
               <hi>And on a day the ſonnes of God came and ſtood before the Lord, and Sathan was alſo among them. Abrahams</hi> ſonnes are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to <hi>ſtarres</hi> and <hi>ſands.</hi> Starres are the heauenly ſonnes of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, as <hi>Iaacob:</hi> Sands are <hi>filij terrae,</hi> ſonnes of the fleſh, earthly proud inhabitants of Babylon, as <hi>Eſau.</hi> Behold it was then <hi>poſterior dies, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lior auis,</hi> the latter day, the better bird. <hi>The elder ſhall ſerue the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Iaacob</hi> did excelle his brother, 1 <hi>iure primogeniturae:</hi> 2 <hi>hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditate terrare ſanctae:</hi> 3 <hi>praerogatiua faederis &amp; Eccleſiae:</hi> In the right of the beſt birthright, inheritance, and couenant. In three faire pre-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minences. In the firſt is ſignified the ſpirit of adoption, by which we are ſealed. In the ſecond, our heauenly countrie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech. 37.</hi> Tacita. Obiect.</note> to which we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. In the third, the life of the Church, out of which there is no life. Here our drie bones are quickned. But let this be true, that thus the elder prerogatiue was faſtened to the younger: yet <hi>(non obſtante)</hi> it could not be true in their ſpecialties, becauſe ſtill the elder did preoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupate iuriſdiction ouer his brother. Yes;<note place="margin">Reſponſ.</note> howſoeuer <hi>Eſau</hi> for a time made a more potent ſhew for prioritie then the yonger, yet was the Prophecie true, both in the letter and the myſterie. In the letter true, for the Idumaeans which were of <hi>Eſaus</hi> iſſues were tributarie to <hi>Dauid</hi> which was of <hi>Iaacobs</hi> generations. Some doe vnderſtand it,<note place="margin">Comeſtor.</note> and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly alſo, that <hi>Eſau</hi> did ſerue <hi>Iaacob,</hi> whilſt he did perſecute him, as the fyle doth ſeruice to the yron, to make it more bright, the fanne ſeruice to the corne to clenſe it, and the furnace ſeruice to the gold to purifie it. The truth is, that <hi>Eſau</hi> did <hi>Iaacob</hi> more good then he meant
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20345:7"/>him, as <hi>Iaacobs</hi> ſonnes by ſelling of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to vilifie him, did promote him to honour. <hi>Deus aliquandiu impiorum indulget petulantiae, ſed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſtatuit &amp; Eccleſiae tandem fontes dilatat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Infideles Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae ruinas in diſcinctis vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dunt vt Q. Fabius naues diuiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do aquis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſit. Sed Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia vt tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhenus lapis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teger enatat.</note> 
               <hi>vt impiorum furores ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ei incommodaſſe appareat quin idem propagaſſe;</hi> God doth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time winke at the iniurious attempts of the preſumptuous, but at his will he doth reſtraine them and inlarge his Church, that her health may ſhine out of the bond of aduerſitie, and her enemies blowes ende in her aduantage. Here I might reioyce, to handle the right hand of Gods prouident power, but I muſt containe my ſelfe within the limits of <hi>Ecce</hi> in this place. See then the truth in the myſterie, aboue the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Iacob</hi> came laſt, but did ouer-flie his brother <hi>Eſau.</hi> Firſt, that which is carnall; then that which is ſpirituall: the old <hi>Adam</hi> came firſt, and the new <hi>Adam</hi> came after: <hi>O melior auis!</hi> The Eagle bird had Eagles wings, and did mount on high aboue his brother. Such is his magnificence, <hi>That the Lord ſaid to my Lord, Sit thou at my right hand, &amp;c.</hi> Such is the ſuperioritie of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> that in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation he had a name giuen him aboue euery name. <hi>The elder muſt ſerue they younger:</hi> and glad may <hi>Adam</hi> bee, that he and his may doe ſeruice to Chriſt; as the ſheaues which did reuerence <hi>Ioſephs</hi> ſheafe: for in <hi>Adam</hi> all die, but in Chriſt are all made aliue. The Schollers of <hi>Pyrene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Myſtae genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.</note> and the wanton heads of the Temple, infamous at Corinth, did obiect that Chriſt died as did <hi>Adam,</hi> the yonger brother as the elder. The Apoſtle graunteth this for truth, that both died, yet the difference of their death is notable. Both died and paid the <hi>wages of ſinne: Sed mors Adae poenae peccati mors Chriſti hoſtia peccati,</hi> The death of <hi>Adam</hi> was the penaltie of ſinne, the death of Chriſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the ſinner. This prepotencie was worth an <hi>Ecce,</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in Chriſt all things are become new, for with his wounds are wee healed.<note place="margin">Fidelis medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus is eſt qui pro infirmo mortiferum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibit remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um vt ſane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur infirmus.</note> And in the reuewe of <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> here is <hi>Ecce</hi> againe, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold white and blacke, good and euill, light and darkeneſſe, life and death in two ſonnes; as if <hi>Rebecca's</hi> breaſts did yeeld two kinds of milke, wholeſome milke for <hi>Iacob,</hi> as the Hebrew mother; corrupt milke for <hi>Eſau,</hi> as the Egyptian nurſe. And now <hi>Rebecca's</hi> breaſts are not like the Equiuocators text, both true and falſe, they are both of one wholeſome taſte, one hallowed kind of milke. The ſecond teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are both one ſincere milke of the word of God, they are both of one truth, and ſpirit of life: as there is but one Lord, faith, baptiſme, hope, and ſaluation. <hi>Chriſtus eſt veritas aeternalis, &amp; verbum eſt veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas normalis,</hi> Chriſt is the eternall eſſentiall truth, and his word is our rule for truth. There is but one God, and one word. <hi>Vnus veritatis
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20345:7"/>fons eſt Deus, &amp; verbum vna veritas in omnes filios ſaliens;</hi> God is the onely fountaine of truth, and his word is the liuing water flowing into his childrens hearts, as the pure riuer of water of life, cleere as Criſtal, proceeding out of the throne of God, and of the Lambe. <hi>Rebecca's</hi> breaſts are one holy Scripture, and all holy Scripture, as one heauenly Canaan, which floweth with milke and hony, of one ſauour and power of life. But whence then is the difference of theſe two brethren? ſhal I climbe vp into Gods throne, and ſit with him among the ſecrets of his incircumſcriptible predeſtination? no, I will reuerence the Arke of his ſecret treaſures, but I will not ſearch it without warrant. Here is <hi>abyſſius imperueſtigabilis,</hi> which S. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth <hi>deepeneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11.33.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> all immenſe, beyond waight and meaſure.</p>
            <p>Here Pride may buſie her ſelfe to doe much hurt, as ſome Epicures,<note place="margin">Nigidius figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus. Eudoxus. Auerrois. <hi>Eſa. 28. 1. Sam. 6. Eccl. 40.</hi> Electos &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probos certo conſilio diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit Deus, illos ad vitam gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis deſtinando hos ad poenaem iuſtè ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do. <hi>Eph. 1.4. Rom. 96.13</hi>
               </note> and other Philoſophers, and other Schoole-men haue done. But woe to the crowne of Pride, her latter end is worſe then the beginning; as the Bethſhemites were ſtricken in their hinder parts. None can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend thoſe ſecrets, more then a man can hold the ſeas in his fiſt, or meaſure heauen, or count the ſands, or waigh the mountaines. If any bold bayard ſhall ſay, there is no preordination, becauſe he cannot fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thome it, it were as if the blind ſhould ſay there is no Sunne, becauſe he cannot ſee it. Let this ſuffice, that God hath choſen his in Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the foundations of the world were laid. If any aske, how? let the Apoſtle anſwer: of his meere good will, foreſtanding all cauſes in our own worthineſſe. God calleth all to the Church, and in eternal and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluble preſcience eſpying veſſels of honour, and wrath; the one ſort is choſen, the other left, as light ware at the ballance: <hi>Thou art waighed in the ballance, and found too light.</hi> Vnto this point is annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the recogitable oddes betwixt the elections of God &amp; man. Thoſe things which man chooſeth, are therefore choſen, becauſe they are waight, but the gold of gods choyce, is therefore waight becauſe it is choſen.</p>
            <p>Thus did God loue and chooſe Iſrael, not becauſe they were better people then other, but they were better, becauſe God did chooſe them: <hi>The Lord thy God hath choſen thee to be a pretious people to himſelfe, &amp;</hi> All Popiſh Atheiſme, and other blaſphemous inſuitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt God, for election and reiection of <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> were ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily daſhed, if I ſhould preferre Gods prerogatiue aboue the Popes. We are certified long ſince,<note place="margin">Diſtinct. <hi>40.</hi> Si Papa.</note> that if the Pope doe carrie many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand with him into hell, no man may be ſo bold as to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trol him <hi>quia cuntos iudicaturus à nemine eſt iudicandus, &amp;c.</hi> Becauſe the Pope
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20345:8"/>may iudge all men, and may not be iudged of any. But I haue no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to idle out my pretious time with ſuch trifles. One thing I haue to ſpeake out of lowly and reueiled knowledge, in the diſcuſſions of the learned, concerning the Bee and the Spider, to manifeſt the worke of grace receiued. Whatſoeuer of the word of God <hi>Iacob</hi> ſuckes, the ſuppe is honie,<note place="margin">Eſa. 55. 2. Cor. 2.16.</note> or wine, or milke, more worth then money, or money worth, all ſanctified, the ſauour of life vnto life. But whatſoeuer <hi>Eſau</hi> ſuckes, it turneth to humour, corrupt, &amp; accurſed, the ſauour of death vnto death.<note place="margin">Ioh. 10. Ioh. 6. Prou. 9.</note> It is not giuen to all to know the voyce of the ſhepheard, to taſte the bread of life, or to ſauour the wine of wiſdome; as many in the ſame garden paſſe many wholſeome hearbes and flowers in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or inſenſibilitie, which others gather in knowledge for ſmell and taſte.<note place="margin">Meierus.</note> 
               <hi>Iudicia Dei credentibus mella ſapiunt, ſed incredulis etiam mellitiſſimae promiſſiones ſunt fellis plenae:</hi> The iudgements of God are an honie combe to the beleeuers, but to the vnbeleeuer the ſweeteſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God are bitterneſſe. If any call to me, to know why I call this bane, humour; <hi>in pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptu cauſa eſt,</hi> for the word is of the ſame faſhion with thoſe euill thoughts, affections, wordes, and deedes, which our countrimen commonly call humours. <hi>Sunt impij vt venenatae quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam beſtiae &amp; ſues bonos odores non ferentes:</hi> The wicked are like ſome venemous and fulſome beaſts, which are ſicke with the breath of wholeſome ſmels.<note place="margin">Deut. 32.</note> 
               <hi>Their vine is of Sodome, the poyſon of dragons, and the cruell gall of Aſpes.</hi> But ſince the wicked ones do thus wilfully fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhew their owne ruine, let thee elect be ſtill gathering more ioy to their conſciences, and reioyce that their names are written in heauen.</p>
            <p>Now then to paſſe on,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.20.</note> leſt I ſhould looſe mine <hi>Ecce</hi> in the plaine field. Behold, the two twins were at ſtrife for the bleſſing, which was a dignity annexed to the birthright, as an excellencie vnited to the crown: whoſoeuer holdeth one for euer, muſt haue both. They ſtroue for the birth-right before their birth, and in the very inſlant the ſtrife continued, for <hi>Iacob</hi> had <hi>Eſau</hi> by the heele. <hi>Signum retardantis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um qui prior erat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 25.26 <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; fatigantis eum qui fortior &amp; praeualentis in certa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine pietatis;</hi> It was a ſigne that the better ſhould ouertake his elder, that the weaker ſhould ouercome the ſtronger, &amp; true pietie win the maſterie of falſe ſanctitie. What was their contention ended with their birth?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen 25.31.</hi> Hemingius. Inaequacior qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Glauci &amp; Diomedis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutatio.</note> no, the ſtrife continued ſtil for the birth-right: <hi>Sel me euen now thy birth-right, and Eſau ſware vnto him, and ſold his birth right vnto Iacob. Eſau</hi> as the foole ſelleth heauen for earth: <hi>Iacob</hi> as the wiſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant buyeth the pearle. Now <hi>Iacob</hi> is become ſonne and heire to the crowne of Gods bleſſings.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:20345:8"/>
            <p> The bleſſing is not yet declared vpon him, but hee is as ſure of the bleſſing as of the birth-right. Thus was the preeminence of bleſſing vpon <hi>Ephraim,</hi> before <hi>Iaacob</hi> laied his right hand on him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.16</note> 
               <hi>(for in the volume of thy booke were all things written, before there was any of them,)</hi> but it was not manifeſt till then.</p>
            <p>A Doctrine of comfort is this to all which haue receiued that ſauing grace which is ſufficient. They are as ſure of glory as they are of grace,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12</note> becauſe glory belongs to grace, as the inheritance to the heire, and the bleſſing to the birth-right; yet ſo, as birth-right, bleſſing, grace, and glory, and all are of Gods gift,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. 6.14</hi> Mercedem o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pibus delitam negamus, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitum fate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, nemo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat deum debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. <hi>4.</hi> talentae quia duo dedit, vel bominibus deberi gloriam quia imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt gratiam. <hi>Mar. 14.25 Leuit. 23.39</hi> Gwerricus Abbas.</note> not of mans merit or worthineſſe by the Law, for ye are not vnder the Law, but vnder grace. The time of glorie is next to the time of grace, in the ſurety of ſucceſsion, as the time of the feaſt was next to the time of the vintage. This is now the time of the vintage, the ſweete wines of the Scripture and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Chriſt and the holy Ghoſt are preſſed out, that after we may drinke anew of the fruit of the vine in the kingdome of God. <hi>When yee haue gathered the fruit of the Land, yee ſhall keepe an holy feast vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord.</hi> This life is the ſeaſon of gathering ſweet grapes of grace, next is the feaſt, the time of glorie. But I muſt remember where I am and bind ſhort all other circumſtantiall tidings together. <hi>Eſau</hi> proud, <hi>Eſau</hi> contemnes his brother <hi>(vt Diobolarem)</hi> as the irefull Woolfe the little Kidde. Hee ſold the title but hee purpoſeth perforce to hold the inheritance. In which example were may take a view of the common Centaures and Cyclopes of the world, which hold al <hi>per fas et nefas,</hi> all by ſtrong hand: hee wil haue all lawfull which is vnlawfull, and will be as the Lion was, his owne caruer. Neither was that <hi>fraus vulpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culae</hi> wanting in <hi>Eſaus</hi> deſignes; for to ſtrengthen himſelfe that hee might be able to beare downe his brother, hee maketh matches with two wiues, without liking, conſent, or knowledge of his parents. He was as the Scrpent, which was more ſubtill then any beaſt of the field, <hi>clandeſtinas aucupatur conſultationes contra iuſtitiam et pacem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Brunus.</note> hee putteth the ſnare of the hunter, to ouerthrow all righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous peace with noyſome peſtilence. This is the man which will bee more wiſe then God, his meaning is otherwiſe then God meant. Hee will match eſpecialy,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 12.7 26.3</note> with the Princes daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Philiſtines, whom the Lord did purpoſe to root out. In theſe coherences hee pretendeth peace with all men. A peaceable man is <hi>Eſau,</hi> hee will haue peace with all the world. It was then with him, as it was long after with the Arrians and other ſucceeding Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rikes, in their ſubtill contriuements: iuſt as it is now with the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20345:9"/>when their ſhew is beſt, their intent is worſt. But all this great haſt to be great,<note place="margin">Oſe 1.7</note> was without good ſpeed; and all his confidence in the fleſh of mans arme is vaine: for he cannot hold that inheritance by bow, or ſword, or battell, or horſes, horſe-men, or kinſ-men; whoſe tenure was not of the willer not runner,<note place="margin">Rom 9.16</note> but of the mercy of God. Much like to this was <hi>Salomons</hi> ſeducement miſcarried with worldly wiſdome, to confidence in carnall power. He concludeth matches with his Aegyptian neighbors, <hi>Moab, Ammon, Edom, Zidon,</hi> and <hi>Heth;</hi> and yet his great ſonne and heire for all his fathers cunning,<note place="margin">3 Reg. 11</note> loſt tenne Tribes at once of his owne kingdome. What ſaith <hi>Roboam</hi> after the extinction of his father?<note place="margin">3 Reg. 12</note> what? My little finger ſhall bee greater then my fathers loines. O <hi>Roboam</hi> by mee Kings reigne, but the armes of the wicked ſhall be broken.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 37.17</note> Afterward when <hi>Salomon</hi> ſlept with his fathers, <hi>Roboam</hi> had a ſmarting feeling of Gods power in the proofe of <hi>Ahijah</hi> his Propheſie.<note place="margin">3 Reg. 11</note> For as the Prophet caught hold on the new garment on <hi>Ieroboams</hi> backe or his owne, and rent it off in twelue peeces; ſo <hi>Roboams</hi> new kingdome was rent from his Scepter, and none followed the houſe of <hi>Dauid,</hi> but the Tribe of <hi>Iudah</hi> only. Had not he cauſe to cry out as he fled to Ieruſalem for <hi>feare, crucior bolum tantum mihi eſſe, ereptum tam ſubito è faucibus;</hi> I am troubled out of meaſure,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.137</note> to ſee my meat in ſpite of my teeth to fall out of my mouth, and my ſelfe vnable to with-hold it: but iuſt art thou O God, and iuſt are thy iudgements. And thus it doth often prooue with them which make their reckoning without God as <hi>Mauritius</hi> did; the caſt of their anchor is preuented, their treaſures are but coales, and their nuts but ſhelles,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 146</note> both their pleaſures and profits are cut ſhort of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts. Therefore truſt not in Princes, nor in any ſonne of man, for there is no helpe in him. Thinke then (if it be thus) that thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepert confederacies of ſurly <hi>Eſau</hi> with Infidels, (both againſt faith and good manners) were as pricking thornes to <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Rebekah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ge. 26.34.35</note> But <hi>Iſaac</hi> after many tedious daies of his weariſome pilgrimage (his eies beeing dimme) expecteth his end, and to ſet his houſe in order before hee die, he diſpoſeth himſelfe to his laſt will and teſtament. He knowing alſo that <hi>Eſau</hi> was numerous in children,<note place="margin">Zeno.</note> and cunning in his plots; and that <hi>Iacob</hi> was both childleſſe, and wifeleſſe, and plain: he doth fully purpoſe to bequeath the great predominancy to the elder brother. <hi>Make me ſauoury meat ſuch as I loue, and bring it to mee that I may eate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 27.4</note> 
               <hi>and that my ſoule may bleſſe thee before I die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By theſe thoughts of <hi>Iſaac</hi> we may perceiue, that God ſeeth not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20345:9"/>as man ſeeth <hi>(ante pedes)</hi> only, for man purpoſeth and God diſpoſeth. All is Gods to diſpoſe or tranſpoſe at his pleaſure, as he tranlſated the Egyptian riches to the Iſraelites hands,<note place="margin">I. Oſorius.</note> that they might handle them better. You know that when <hi>Iaacob</hi> was to bleſſe his ſonne <hi>Ioſephs</hi> two ſonnes, ſo that his right hand was vpon the yonger ſonne, and his left hand on the elder: <hi>incongrua videbatur illa manuum impoſitio Ioſepho ignaro prouidentiae Dei,</hi> that impoſition of hands which was orderred by Gods prouidence, looked like an iniurious fact to <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> not beeing at that time acquainted with Gods purpoſe: <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did thinke his aged father was in feebleneſſe and error,<note place="margin">Gen. 48.17 <hi>Iunilius.</hi>
               </note> and would haue changed his hands. Surely a good man was <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and a Prophet, but not alwaies enlightened alike with the ſpirit of propheſie, nor for all things; therefore his father beeing better guided with a ſuperior de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of light at that time, continueth his bleſſing, and createth <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im</hi> the ſon of his right hand:<note place="margin">Gen. 48.19</note> So that as then the primacy was giuen to the younger brother,<note place="margin">Prouidentia Dei eſt ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio aptorum mediorum ad finem.</note> contrary to the fathers deſire (the Lord ruling the lots) thus muſt it now be, by the diſpoſition of the ſame power. And now it is plaine, that <hi>Eſau</hi> hath met with his match; hee is wily for himſelfe, but God is of counſell with <hi>Iaacob.</hi> Looke vpon the contriuement; <hi>Eſau</hi> is ſent on hunting whiles <hi>Iaacob</hi> taketh the prey <hi>(coruum deluſit hiantem)</hi> and is inſtauled into the bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Heere let <hi>Eſau</hi> complaine that hee hath waried himſelf in the waies of wickedneſſe, drawing out the cords of vanitie,<note place="margin">Quid niſi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis dolor. <hi>Eſay 59.5 Luke 5.5</hi>
               </note> and weauing the Spiders web, and at length is become as the fiſhers, which labored all night and caught nothing. In a word, theſe words of my text lap in the reaſon of inducement to <hi>Iſaac</hi> to doe that which he meant not to haue done. The Lord is ſuch a conſiderate and powerfull agent in the buſineſſe, that <hi>Iſaac</hi> doth cheerefull beſtow that good turne on <hi>Iaacob</hi> which hee reſerued for <hi>Eſau.</hi> Why ſo?<note place="margin">S. Bernard. Odor Chriſti ſentitur ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> videatur, vt corpus aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticum ante patres, et poſt filios emittit odores.</note> becauſe hee did not ſmell of the rankneſſe of the ſheep-coate, but of the pleaſures of the field.</p>
            <p>The bleſſing doth conſiſt of two reſpects, as a garden of pleaſant fruit, and delicious ſmell. Heere are praiers for <hi>Iaccob</hi> in propheſies, and promiſes of his ſweete and wholſome fruites: And heere is the praiſe of <hi>Iaccob</hi> for his delightfull ſmell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſaac</hi> his motiue, whereby he was inuited to bleſſe <hi>Iaccob,</hi> is plaine in theſe words: <hi>Behold, the ſmell of my ſonne is as the ſmell of a field, which the Lord hath bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now after all this inference of <hi>Ecce,</hi> it may bee ſaid to me as once it was to the Citizens of <hi>Myndus: viri Myndij claudite portas,</hi> ſhut your
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20345:10"/>gates leaſt your City runne out at your mouth, and your little cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration vaniſh through your great heat. Indeed a great gate may be too wide for a little pingle; but albeit I cannot now cut my doore leſſe, yet I may well inlarge this garden plot to make it greater, ſo may the proportion be more equall.</p>
            <p>Firſt then to fit and finiſh vp this portall, <hi>Ecce</hi> behold: The word is very ſpecious in the original <hi>Ree,</hi> and in the tranſlation <hi>vide,</hi> but commonly <hi>Ecce,</hi> as if the meaning were to call all the world to come and ſee,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.46.</note> as <hi>Philip</hi> called <hi>Nathanael</hi> to Chriſt, come and ſee. The word is ſometime of oſtenſion, ſometime of admiration, and ſometime of both. Oſtenſion is againe two fold, by their counterfeit ſhadow, or true exhibition. Of counterfeit ſhadow; as behold heere is Chriſt, and there is Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.</note> a counterfeit ſhadow: of true exhibition: as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Lamb of God,<note place="margin">John 1.</note> O true exhibition. Sometime <hi>Ecce</hi> is of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and ſtands at a gaze, and doth gaze at a wonder: behold a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin ſhal beare a ſonne, <hi>miraculum mirabiliter mirabile;</hi> a virgins childe and God and man, both one, a light of all maruelles. A man ſo weak that he muſt die,<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.3.</note> a God ſo ſtrong that he could conquer death: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, there brake he the arrows of the bow, the ſhield, the ſword, and the battell. <hi>Selah</hi> Behold a wonder. In ſome places this Aduereb <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce</hi> is of admiration and demonſtration both together, and diuerſly of diuers ſtrangers, either difficult, or new, or ſudden.</p>
            <p>Now may you ſtand vpon the top of <hi>Ecce</hi> as vpon a mount, and behold all the pleaſures of this text, as the plaine of Iordan watered e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiy where. Firſt the difficulty of this <hi>Ecce</hi> is note worthy that euer <hi>Iacob</hi> could riſe to this bleſſing, Chriſt aſcend to his glory, and the Prince of Wales attaine to his Principality.</p>
            <p>Where was the <hi>Ecce</hi> of <hi>Iacob</hi> when his father <hi>Iſaac</hi> was in offering for ſacrifice,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 22. Gen. 27.41.</note> or whileſt his brother <hi>Eſaus</hi> Vow ſtood on foot to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice his brothers bloud to his fathers funeralles: <hi>The daies will come ſhortly of mourning for my father<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> where was the <hi>Ecce</hi> of Chriſt, the glory and riches of his God-head,<note place="margin">Difficultate partes pericli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur eccleſia, ſed euincuntur hoſtes vt Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gones a Perſio, vel verius vt Draco a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chacle</note> when as the Serpent in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, he was lift vp vpon the croſſe, and one of the ſouldiers with a ſpeare pierſed his ſide?</p>
            <p>Where was the <hi>Ecce</hi> of the Prince, when the Lion and the Lions Whelp were vowed to the maſſacre, <hi>inconſpiratione pluſqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Catilinaria</hi> in the gun powder-treaſon. Wee doe read of <hi>Catiline</hi> that firebrand of old, that to faſten his confederates in their mercileſſe intent, he did mingle mans bloud with wine, as <hi>Pilate</hi> mingled the bloud of the Galileans with their owne facrifice. This drinke thus prepared, hee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20345:10"/>carried vp and downe, to his partners, as the Prieſts of Rome doe now beare their hoaſt and conſecrated wedges, heere and there to their abetters. When he came to place and company fit to his purpoſe, he did in this drinke carowſe and ſwallow vp his impious vow: In this draught all his aſſociates muſt follow him, to make their ſword drunke with the bloud of their Country, and wholly to ſubuert the preſent glory of Rome.</p>
            <p>But this monſtrous <hi>Catilines</hi> brood among vs,<note place="margin">Iob. 31.33.</note> was more mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous in eating and drinking, (as they ſuppoſed) the blood of Chriſt, to ratifie their vowes, concealing iniquity in their boſomes. Thus they did bind themſelues in an holy league, like Romane Saints of theſe daies, to reioice together for the finall expiration of King and Prince, and the mournfull deſolation of Church &amp; common wealth. So euery man may ſee, how our <hi>Ecce</hi> hath eſcaped fire and ſword (by God mercie) for the honour and ioy of England.</p>
            <p>But is it difficultie alone? no, it is noucltie alſo. There are nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties paſt in the holy Teſtament, nouelties preſent in the new children of regeneration, and nouelties to come in the ſtole of glorie. The new Teſtament was a noueltie: the Lord had written the old law in tables of ſtone, but that the penne of the Writer ſhould indite a law in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts of mans heart, this was worth an <hi>Ecce. Nouitas amaena,</hi> ful of delicate and healthfull pleaſure. <hi>Behold the daies come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 31.31.</note> 
               <hi>that I will make a new couenant, &amp;c. The wiſe man ſaid in his time, there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing new vnder the ſunne, yet euery regenerate man, yong or old,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>is a new creature.</hi> Both theſe are true, becauſe our new birth is not of earth, but of heauen, not of mortall ſeed, but of immortall,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.23.</note> aboue the Sunne. All the adopted ſonnes of God, are borne, not of the will of the fleſh, nor of the will of man; but of the will of God, our new birth is aboue the Sunne.</p>
            <p>Thus is <hi>Iacob</hi> a new man, a new creature in Chriſt: <hi>O Chriſt Ieſus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. 8. Pſal. 65.11.</hi> Vt ignus fortis forti flatu for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatim.</note> 
               <hi>all my freſh ſprings ſhall be in thee, for thy ſteps droppe fatneſſe.</hi> Thus is the Prince, a Prince of God, <hi>Abner</hi> his fathers candle lightened with fire from the Altar, whoſe ſweet conditions, tempered with the oyle of grace, beare witneſſe, that he is not onely borne of an earthly king be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, but borne againe of an heauenly King aboue; that the King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, and the king belowe, may both reioyce in their ſonne: <hi>Behold the ſmalle of my ſonne, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Ecce</hi> againe, behold a ſuddaine ioy: ſometimes wonderfull things breake out of their cloſets, as lightening out of the clouds, when there is not any expectation or hope attending; and ſometimes when
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20345:11"/>deſire more or leſſe is waiting for their appearance. Of the firſt ſort was the ſuddaine light which came downe from heauen, outward, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the face of <hi>Saul</hi> to aſtoniſh him;<note place="margin">Act 9.</note> inward, into the heart of <hi>Saul,</hi> to conuert him; that of him it is rightly ſaid, <hi>Tamſubito Cygnus qui modo conſonus erat:</hi> Who could perſwade himſelfe, that a crow in a trice could be turned into a ſwanne. Of the ſecond ſort, was that light of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and the ſpirit of God.<note place="margin">Luc. 24.4. Act 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>There were ſome looking for Chriſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold two men ſtood ſuddainely before them in ſhining veſtures. There were ſome looking on Chriſt, and behold a light did ſhine ſuddainly from heauen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> 
               <hi>There were ſome gathered in daily expectation of the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (whom Chriſt promiſed to ſend) and ſuddainly there came a ſound from heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neſcit tarda molimma, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia. S. S.</note> 
               <hi>as of a ruſhing and a mightie wind.</hi> What then, came thoſe illuſtrious meſſages without hope, or no? Indeed hope was much wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened, as one trauailing long is wearie; but it did but ſeem weake, they hoped ſtill for that vigorous reſurrection, they looked ſtill for that glorious aſcenſion, they longed ſtill for the gladſome comming of the holy Ghoſt.<note place="margin">Beda.</note> Yet all thoſe maruellous, vertuous, famous workes were ſuddaine. As wee all looke for that hopefull appearing of the Iudge of quicke and dead (and how long ſoeuer his ſtay may be, with whom a thouſand yeares are but as a day) hope maketh not to be aſhamed,<note place="margin">Spes eſt ſancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum baculus, de quo ſuſtinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ne cadant, &amp; ſuſtenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur ne deficiant. <hi>Matth. 24.27.</hi>
               </note> yet for all our ſerious vigilancie commanded, it ſhall be ſuddaine: <hi>As the lightening which flieth from the Eaſt to the Weſt, ſo ſhall the comming of the ſonne of man be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O bleſſed <hi>Iacob,</hi> thy long promiſed bleſſing is come ſuddainely, in a day thou thoughteſt not: our bleſſed Sauiour annointed with the oyle of grace aboue his fellowes, was long and often foretold, yet is his comming exceeding ſuddaine: <hi>Therefore call his name, make haſte, make ſpeed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 8.</note> 
               <hi>ſpeed to the pray, and haſte to the ſpoile.</hi> Our gracious Prince his honour hath ſtated long in the glowing eares of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, whoſe eies burned with zealous deſire to behold it. <hi>And behold of a ſuddaine the ſmell of my ſonne.</hi> This is the ſtemme of honour for which great Britaine did ſacrifice their daily prayers, our bounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queene did breath out her iuſt deſires, our renowmed king did yeeld his ſacred promiſe; and now of a ſuddaine is that ioyfull day come, the day of playing of Organes, of ſinging of birds and ſounding of Trumpets. Now is the day come, in which king <hi>Iames</hi> doth pay his vowes, his vowes to God, his right to the Prince, his honour to the Land, his fauour to the ſubiect, his word to the Queene, <hi>aſſuredly thy ſonne Salomon ſhall raigne after me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Reg. 3.30.</note> 
               <hi>O King liue for euer. Vita homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſabillum animae,</hi> The life of man is but a ſmall point, and hath ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20345:11"/>hold on earth. <hi>Lex mortis firma non abrogatur, mutatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Boſquier.</note> 
               <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſatur, &amp;c.</hi> Deaths doome is bound vp ſo faſt that it cannot bee looſed. It is ſet downe that euery man muſt die once: <hi>Seriùs ant citius mortem properamus ad vnam:</hi> I am perſwaded,<note place="margin">Serniamus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi precibus, qui ſeruit Deo legibus.</note> that neither Queene, nor Prince, nor any Impe royall, that none truely noble or gentle, or true Chriſtian, deſireth to ſee thy laſt day. Yet is mans life but a ſpan long, and now here is a pawne for the ſtate, a nurſerie for grace, the ſtandard to religion, a beautie to the crowne, the peace, health, and wealth of the land; this is <hi>Salomon</hi> the Kings ſonne. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the ſmell of my ſonne is as the ſmell of a field, which the Lord hath bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for <hi>Ecce,</hi> the head of the Text, and head of the ſprings: <hi>Behold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to <hi>the Smell,</hi> the firſt riuer of the head. Here might I ſhew you many delightſome turnings to many wholeſome walks in this word. There is <hi>odor merus &amp; metaphoricus.</hi> Againe, <hi>odor metaphoricus eſt Chriſtiaut Chriſtianorum.</hi> But I muſt neceſſarily paſſe by theſe paths, till I find other oportunitie, and more leiſure. The common partiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Odour</hi> is into good and euill; but what haue wee to doe with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill? <hi>Quid argijs cum ſacrificijs, quid canibus cum ſanctis:</hi> There is no communion betwixt God and <hi>Belial: without ſhalbe dogges and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 21.</note> 
               <hi>all their ſmell is of the ſulphure of Sodome. Et ſi doctores illi ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiſſimi &amp; ductores aulici porcos obſcaene defaedatos ne vno digitorum oſtendant aut verbulo corripiant, quid ego miſer homuncio aut Balaami aſinus.</hi> I know that bookes and ſermons, which are admonitions of other mens faults, as the blacke bill, are exceeding neceſſarie in theſe times of darkeneſſe; but they are all out of my way. All our labour here ſhould bee ſpent in ſearching out the good Odours of <hi>Iacob,</hi> Chriſt, and the Prince: and thrice happy both they, which haue Chriſt the ſauour of life betwixt them. All their ſweet ſmell is of the ſauour of his oyntments. <hi>O bleſſed Sauiour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2.3. Cant. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>theſe are the virgins which delight in thy ſauour: Thy name is as an oyntment powred out, therefore the virgins loue thee.</hi> But it is high time to diſtinguiſh of good Odours.</p>
            <p>There is a good odour of pietie, a ſweet ſacrifice,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.18. 2. Cor. 2.15. 2. Cor. 2.14.</note> a good odour of good report: ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> his name had a good ſmell, a good odour of the Goſpel: ſo is it a garland all of ſweet flowers, a good odour of zealous prayer: ſo is it as the perfume of the Cenſor.<note place="margin">Apoc. 8.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Shall I tell you more, what a ſauour is there where all theſe meet in one ſoule, as the incenſe of one altar; pure religion, ſweet conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, true faith, and holy loue, they are altogether as the offering of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20345:12"/>
               <hi>Noahs</hi> Altar. <hi>And Noah built an Altar to the Lord, and tooke of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery cleane beaſt and of euery cleane bird, and offered burnt offerings to the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 8</note> How them? what was the iſſue? Reade further: <hi>and the Lord ſmelled a ſauour of reſt.</hi> Such is the ſmell of all faithfull hearts as the ſmell of <hi>Noahs</hi> Altar to the Lord: <hi>Iaacobs</hi> heart is as <hi>Noahs</hi> Altar. Behold the ſmell of my ſonne. But I haue more in my way of my poore readings, in which I find good odours of many diſtributions. There is one ſmell of the flower of the Vine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S.</hi> Gregorie.</note> another of the Oliue, of the Roſe, of the Lilly, of the Violet, and of the Corne-eare; and all ſweet.</p>
            <p>The Vine is Faith, the Oliue is Victory, the Roſe is Charity, the Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie is Chaſtity, the Violet is Humility, the Corne-eare is many cornes, good workes in their ripeneſſe all in one odour. Such Vines, and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liues, and Roſes, and Lillies, and Violets, and Corne-eares were the <hi>Philippians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.18</note> an odour that ſmelleth ſweet, a ſacrifice acceptable and pleaſant to God. Such as <hi>Iſrael</hi> whilſt the dew was vpon him, <hi>hee ſhall grow as the Lillie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oſe. 14.6.7</note> 
               <hi>and faſten his roots as the trees of Lebanon: his beauty ſhall be as the Oliue tree, and his ſmell as Lebanon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iaacob</hi> had the Vine, true faith in his heart, his father <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith: not an <hi>agnus Dei</hi> about his necke, or hanging in a tablet at his breſt,<note place="margin">Fides purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans cor, eſt vna, integra, vera, viua. <hi>Ioh. 12.3</hi>
               </note> as ſome abuſed Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpell; but a ſound faith growing within and without his heart, all his affections as the branches of a vine, for his Sauiour all the vine as a bower to reſt in, and all the bower as the houſe filled with ſweet ſauour: what a ſmell is the ſmell of this vine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iacob</hi> had the Oliue victory in his faith,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.13</note> againſt all Principalities, and powers of darkneſſe: hee was ſhort of Chriſt in reſpect of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time, but he had the ſubſtance which cheered his heart at all times, with thoughts of his Captaine the <hi>Siloe,</hi> the Conquerer, the Lion,<note place="margin">Gen. 49</note> whoſe paw ſhould be in the necke of his enemies. By this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Iaacob</hi> wanne the victory of the world, ſo ſweete is the ſmell of this Oile.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iacob</hi> had the Roſe-loue in his faith,<note place="margin">Ezek. 47</note> whoſe leaues did not fade, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible loue as appeareth by his wreſtling. Let me be gone (ſaith the Angel) for the morning appeareth.<note place="margin">Geneſ. 32</note> What? let thee goe, my life and my glory; I will not let thee goe vnleſſe thou bleſſe mee. Lord let me loue the ſmell of this Roſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iacob</hi> had a Lilly chaſtity, in his faith a faire Lilly, within the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of his paradiſe,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 50.8</note> as the Lillies by the ſprings of waters; white as the light, and faire without ſpot. His brother haſtened to his Canani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20345:12"/>women, and ſent an ill ſent into the ſoules of his parents; yet <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> kept his <hi>veſſell in holineſſe.</hi> O honour, let me counſell you all to keep the ſmell of this Lilly.<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4 4</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iacob</hi> had the Violet, humble deuotion, in his faith the Violet groweth low by the ground, ſo doth humble deuotion to daily praiers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bartholomaes</hi> Gen. 17.3 1 Sam. 1.13</note> as <hi>Abraham</hi> fell vpon his face, and <hi>Hannah</hi> was humbled before the Lord. Shall I ſtay you a while, to heare <hi>Iaacobs</hi> daily praiers. All yee which liue in plenty or ſcarſity, remember <hi>Iaacobs</hi> Vow. Wee are all in our iourny as <hi>Iaacob</hi> was, and deſirous as hee to come to our fathers houſe, our father wich is in heauen. <hi>Iaacob</hi> vowed a Vow, ſaying,<note place="margin">Gen. 28.20</note> 
               <hi>If God will be with me, and will keepe me in my iourney which I go, and will giue mee bread to eat and cloathes to put on, ſo that I come againe to my fathers houſe in ſafetie, then ſhall the Lord be my God.</hi> Here was ſweet contentment in a lowly eſtate: humble contentation was <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſtaffe, which did flouriſh all with Violets, as <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod did but with flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and almonds; with this ſtaffe came I ouer Iordane. Surely there is an wholeſome breath in the ſmell of this Violet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iaacob</hi> had the corne eare the fruites of faith,<note place="margin">Nomb 17.8 Gen. 32.10 Gal. 5 Gen. 41.5</note> thoſe praiſe-worthy fruites of the ſpirit, Loue, Ioy, Peace, Long Suffering, Meekneſſe, Temperance, Goodneſſe, all ſpecious vpon one faith; as thoſe ſeuen eares of corne ranke and goodly all vpon one ſtalke. Shall I make bold to inuite you all to taſte this corne, for the ſmell of this corne eare.</p>
            <p>Now Prince of Wales, where is thy ſmell? Haſt thou neither Vine, Oliue, Roſe, Lilly, Violet, nor Corne-eare? Surely then thou art a poore Prince, and they are poore whom God hateth: Behold here, the ſmell of the fauour of God to the Prince. The Prince hath them all as <hi>Iacob</hi> had them, he is all Suckoth, Suckoth as the Tabernacles of God, his eies, eares, lippes, heart, all Suckoth; Tents of godlineſſe, pitched in Rephidim the manſion of the medicines of Gods bleſſings. The Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers deſcribe an houſe of deſier: <hi>non quidem, opulentam et ambitioſam,</hi> ſtuffed with the pelfe of the world, and faced with proud ambition: No, <hi>ſed cui nihil teſtit in ſe ſupellectilis,</hi> with workes not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of neceſſarie vſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Behold, here is that houſe as that happy little world all furniſhed with neceſſaries. And here is one thing more then all thoſe neceſſaries and more worth,<note place="margin">Luke 10.42 John 13.1</note> that one thing which is neceſſary and cannot be taken from him. <hi>For whom God loueth hee loueth to the end.</hi> This the ſmell of my ſonne.</p>
            <p>The Prince hath the Vine, the Goſpell in his faith: it is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in which he doth daily refreſh his ſoule; it is the lauour through
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20345:13"/>which he doth daily waſh himſelfe. This is his Baſon and Ewre of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the Goſpel is the Ewre, his heart the Baſon.</p>
            <p>This is a Princely Bath, the Kings Bath all perfumed with health, all with ſauing health. Let young and old, and all waſh themſelues in this Bath. Knights of the Bath, all the which are ſouldiers in this mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant life, vnder the banner of Ieſus Chriſt. Chriſt is the Prince, who gaue himſelfe,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.26.</note> that he might ſanctifie you and clenſe you, by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of water, through the word. The Prince is knight of the order of the comely order of King <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 4.15.</note> waſhed in the ſprings of Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, perfumed with Spikenard, Saffron, Calamus, Cynamon, and all ſweet ſpices.<note place="margin">Cant. 4 2.</note> Knights of the Bath, come forth like a flocke of ſheep, in good order, which goe vp from the waſhing: come forth, as the daughters of Sion, and behold King <hi>Salomon</hi> with the crowne, in the day of the gladneſſe of his heart. Knights of the Bath, come forth, and behold your Prince, let him be your looking glaſſe, as the ruiers of waters are to the faire doues waſhed with milke. The Prince is ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed and waſhed in lordan ſeuen times, the leproſie and luxurie which doth commonly cleaue to the youth of our age, euen to the ſides of their houſe, is waſhed away.</p>
            <p>It is written of <hi>Otho,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suetonius.</note> one of the Emperours, that hee repaired often to his glaſſe to ſee his face, that he might keepe it cleane. The Prince (as report telleth vs) goeth often to his glaſſe, the ſtreames of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of life,<note place="margin">Pſal. 23.</note> the ſtill ſtreames where <hi>Dauid</hi> walked. Indeed <hi>Dauid</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them waters of comforts, right worthy of that title, where he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued himſelfe ſaued, by the waſhing of the new birth, in the blood of the vine.</p>
            <p>Thus is the Prince waſhed,<note place="margin">Tit. 3.5.</note> his heart clenſed, his affections purified, his delights ſanctified,<note place="margin">Nobilitas mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum plus ornot quam genitoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> all like cluſters of the vine: who would not ſmel at the ſmell of this vine?</p>
            <p>The Prince hath the Oliue victorie in his faith, victorious holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. It was told vs long, our eyes were bleſſed with the ſight of our moſt prudent King, that he hath the print of a Lyon vpon him: I doe beleeue it, though I did neuer ſee it, that the Lyon of the tribe of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> is printed vpon him; he hath put on Chriſt. And loe, here is a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againe, the print of a lyon, the ſonne of his father; the rpint of a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the image of Chriſt, which the moſt gracious Saints doe reioyce to be. But where is the Lyons victorie? where but in the conqueſt of the Lyon of <hi>Iudah? Thankes be vnto God, who hath giuen vs victorie in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord:</hi> maſterie againſt the ſinnes of the world, ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of Satan, buffets of the fleſh, blaſphemy, intemperancie, ſcorne,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20345:13"/>ire, reuenge, all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſerpents brood, yet all killed in ſhell; all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, as wormes in the fruit, yet all caſt away in the budde; the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents are quelled, the ſweet bud remaineth: who will not trie the ſmel of this Oliue?</p>
            <p>The Prince hath the Roſe loue in his faith, a bleſſed roſe, a faire complection, the complexion of the faireſt, the beuty of the Church, the colours of Chriſt, the white roſe and the red: <hi>My beloued is white and redde, the chiefeſt of ten thouſand.</hi> There are diuers kinds of loue, as the loue of nature, ſo loue birds one another; loue of conſanguini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſo loue kinſmen; loue of reaſon, ſo loue heathens; loue of grace, ſo loue Chriſtians, which both loue God, and one another. The Princes roſe is Chriſtian loue, the cheerefull loue of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid, that loue maketh a man ſtrong, rich, and wiſe, and here it is prooued; for the Prince his loue hath done marueilous things for him, whereof we reioyce. His loue is ſo ſtrong, that with no ſtrength of the old Sathans, he can be pulled from the truth: <hi>Omnia vincit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor.</hi> His light ſo light, it cannot bee turned into darkeneſſe. His loue ſo rich, ſet with the pearles of Gods fauours, and beſet with the hearts of the thouſands of Iſrael, that he himſelfe is as the chiefeſt of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> who in all things were made rich, and they all reioyce to thinke on all places whereon the ſoles of his feet doe tread. His loue ſo wiſe, that he needeth not any man to teach him, his annoynting teacheth him all things.</p>
            <p>It is written of <hi>Alexander,</hi> that hee had a pretious ſtone, which ſo long as he kept it, did preſerue him from poyſon. I paſſe the credit of that ſtorie, and am well pleaſed to behold the Princes roſe, which the roſe of roſes hath giuen him for a preſeruatiue againſt poyſon. No in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted tokens of Egyptian wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can deceiue him, no mincing, equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uncating purſenets of thoſe Prieſts can catch him. <hi>Schaenobitae</hi> were of old Sophiſticall old women, which to ſeeme faire, painted all their ſpots, and filled vp the wrinckles with ſmooth oyle. And now are the <hi>Schaenobitae</hi> a liue againe, Ieſuits in their faſhion, to put all out of good faſhion, Romiſh, Spaniſh, French, Flemiſh, Engliſh <hi>Schaenobitae,</hi> yet here they looſe their lanthornes. <hi>Pauones ſunt,</hi> ſome ſay they are Peacocks, becauſe they haue colours of an angel, the pace of a theefe, and the voyce of a deuill.</p>
            <p>Theſe birds haue ſit ſo long in ſuch eaſe on their neſts, in the darke places of the kingdome, that they haue hatched here many birds of their owne feather. What are they? Gentlemen, and Ladies, and their followers, Peacockes birds, begot with child with many children,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20345:14"/>ſinnes, and errors, treacheries of that Peacocke of Rome. Thus are there among vs many wiues and children of fornication. O ſay theſe of their dammes,<note place="margin">Oſe 1.2.</note> who cannot be taken, their lippes droppe hony combes.<note place="margin">Prou. 5.3. verſ. 4.</note> O ſay we, who dare bee taken, their end is bitter as worme-wood, and ſharpe as a two edged ſword. Theſe are <hi>Lamiae,</hi> witches, which kill thoſe which ſucke their milke, <hi>Lamiae</hi> tranſlated dragons; <hi>the dragons drawe out their breaſts:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 4.3.</note> many in <hi>Campions</hi> time here in England,<note place="margin">Amos 3.</note> did flie to him, as birds to the fowler, and are taken: <hi>Can a bird be taken in the ſnare if there be no fowler?</hi> Let mee ſpeake to all our skilfull women, which haue turned after <hi>Baal,</hi> and made <hi>Baalbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rith</hi> their God. I would aske this queſtion, what are your Prieſts? and ſay you, you Clergie men in England are <hi>vultures and cormorants,</hi> but our holy Prieſts are harmeleſſe gnats. It is true deare Ladies, for our part, that in ſome things we ſin all, as yours do, and we arrogate no ſuper-arrogant perfections as yours doe: when we haue done all, wee are vnprofitable ſeruants, wee are all compaſſed with our infirmities, as the Prieſts were of old, which were better then your prieſts: and for the ſinnes ſake, we are bound to offer for ſins, as well for our own part, as for the people.<note place="margin">Heb. 5.2, 3.</note> As for your prieſts, wee grant that it is as true alſo, they are your gnats, which humme about your eares, with lullabies of Securitie to your conſciences. They are gnats indeed, and ſo, if they be not bruized as they fall, or caught flying, they ſing till they ſting; and then as the Waſpes, when they haue thruſt in their pikes, they flie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your reſt is gone and your peace diſeaſed.<note place="margin">Thus ſaid a Camaeleon la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>Campi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </note> Heare one of thoſe Oſtriges ſound in your eares, <hi>O tongue of an Angel.</hi> You may call him <hi>Barachel,</hi> all bleſſing, and bowing the knee to God. His name may be <hi>Barionah,</hi> the ſonne of a Doue, all ſpirit of meek eneſſe, <hi>Seruus ſeruorum,</hi> he will lie like a ſtrawe at your foote till the blaſt come. <hi>Vt vipera curuando, ſic iſte humiliando ingreditur:</hi> As a viper enters his crannie by bowing, ſo theſe enter your hearts by crowching. But though he ſpeake fauourably,<note place="margin">Prou. 26.2.5</note> beleeue him not, for there are ſeuen ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations in his heart. His name is <hi>minorum minimus,</hi> The leaſt of the Apoſtles: O gentle heart: the <hi>minorite</hi> is <hi>minimus</hi> indeed, <hi>vt mus in panario,</hi> or as the mouſe in the garner, which miniſheth the fineſt flower, and leaueth the brans for them which maintaine them. They loue to liue like miſe and rattes in many mens houſes, alwaies to their hurt,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.31.</note> where they fare beſt. Theſe are Satans ſiſters, and <hi>Peter,</hi> Satan hath deſired to ſift thee; and at length, this ſonne of a Doue doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an Harpie in the Church, <hi>Bar-Ionah</hi> is changed into <hi>Barnabas a thiefe and a murtherer.</hi> Their brotherhood doth compaſſe our gallant
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20345:14"/>heads like a crowne of roſe-buds; but in the end it prooueth a crowne of thornes. Thus might ye all haue reported, man, wife, and child, one to another, of their brotherhood, <hi>if their ſpirit had ſped at Weſtminſter. Ahohi my brother is my thiſtle and my thorne.</hi> Theſe are your ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers, theſe <hi>Cymerij,</hi> they neuer ſee the ſunne, they will not depart from vs, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy waies. Theſe make all their Proſelytes <hi>Cimerios,</hi> they neuer ſee the ſunne, they cannot,<note place="margin">Iob. 21.14.</note> they are carried hudwincked: a lamentable eſtate of ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, they ſhall neuer depart out of darkenes. Yet theſe <hi>Cymerij,</hi> as we reade of others, haue as they thinke, images of the ſunne, and pictures which are their gods, of aduantage, by tradition, vpon-truſt, onely beleeue as the Church beleeueth. If theſe holy Catholikes thus deuoted to images, doe by miſchance looſe their gods, alacke good people, it fareth with them impatiently, as it was with <hi>Laban.</hi> He ſearched <hi>Iacobs</hi> tent, and <hi>Leahs,</hi> and that of the two handmaids, and laſt of all <hi>Rachels.</hi> Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed poore <hi>Laban,</hi> his daughter had a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s excuſe ready to diſappoint him, that neither could hee finde his gods, nor his gods finde him. Surely his gods were dead, or in <hi>Endimeons</hi> ſleepe, or at the leaſt in a ſlumber with <hi>Epimenides,</hi> that they could not hearken to their ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, no more then <hi>Baal</hi> to his prieſts. Yet for all thoſe infirmities of their gods, theſe holy fathers proclaime openly to their children, <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia bene,</hi> all their pariſhioners are in good health, and they ſay priuate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to themſelues, <hi>A ha, I haue warmed my ſelfe:</hi> loe theſe are our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies pretious gods.</p>
            <p>If I had skill in their tongue, I could call them Pedlers in French, <hi>dicunt album &amp; intendunt nigrum;</hi> they haue an heart and an heart,<note place="margin">Oſe 10.2.</note> like thoſe Partridges of Paphlagonia, neither one haunt, nor one way, for their haunt is diuided. There is a queſtion anciently deſcended, and eaſily anſwered: Why there are ſo many ſheep, and ſo few wolues, ſince men and wolues doe eate ſheepe. Indeed the loue of man to mans profit, is a ſingular preſeruatiue to ſheepe. But now the queſtion is croſſe, why the wolues in creaſe, and the ſheepe decreaſe? <hi>Iamdiu in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oleuit quaerela de millibus ouium, &amp; vnitatibus hominum, ſed noſtra in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertur de vnitatibus ouium, inter mille hominum.</hi> Their complaint in the common wealth, is of the pluralities of ſheepe, and the nullities of men; but our moane which is made in the Puritane countie of North-hampton (as it hath beene nicknamed) is for our decaied flockes of ſheepe, and our multiplied heards of wolues. Shall I reade the cauſe? <hi>Foelix qui potuit,</hi> I haue no ſuch skill; yet would I gueſſe at two cauſes. The one is, of the aduerſarie againſt man; the other, of man againſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20345:15"/>himſelfe.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8.</note> Sathan our aduerſarie hath more care, paines, watches, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, for breeding and nouriſhing of Wolues, then ours is for the proſperity of the people of Gods paſture,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 95.7</note> and ſheep of his hands. And more then ſo, our conniuencie either to ſeeme not to ſee, or to ſee on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when we liſt, or to ſee ſome thing and do nothing, is to ſhake hands with Sathan, <hi>in connubio malorum,</hi> that their <hi>combinations are daily ſtronger,</hi> and are chriſtian connexions more weake? Giue the holy Prophet leaue to ſpeake in this caſe.<note place="margin">Eſay 26.10</note> 
               <hi>Let mercy bee ſhewed to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, yet hee will not learne righteouſneſſe, no more then the Hogge man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, with a chaine of Pearles about his necke.</hi> I would willingly ſpeake here,<note place="margin">Rom. 3</note> what the Apoſtle hath ſpoken, both of <hi>Authores et fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores,</hi> how they are both guiltie.<note place="margin">Methodus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſionis.</note> Or if any angry Pope-ling ſhould cauill, I would wipe of his blow with their owne verdict, which wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth how many waies one man may bee faulty in an other mans fault.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Conſulo, praecipio, conſentio, prouoco, laudo,</l>
               <l>Non retego culpam, non punio, non reprehendo:</l>
               <l>Participo, defendo: meum in caput iſta redundant.</l>
            </q>
            <p>All excuſes of ancient acquaintance are but idle pretenſes in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, <hi>miſeratio effaeminata:</hi> and I thinke it hath beene called fooliſh loue, to nouriſh a Serpent in the boſome, or to ſuffer Wolues to breed in the Wood to waſt Sheepe.<note place="margin">Vt iugulent ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines ſurgunt de nocte latro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> Our predeceſſour could ſay: <hi>odimus accipitre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui ſemper viuit in armis,</hi> who can once loue the Kite, which euer liues in ſpite? I pray you what are the liues of the Remiſh wolues? but fier and ſword, warre and bloud-ſhed. Fare and ſoftly, <hi>Ieſuitae faces Romanae:</hi> Surely, you Engliſh Clergy play the Iauelles with vs, <hi>per hoc Ly.</hi> For thoſe holy Votariſts are goodly torches ſent hither to enlighten our darke thoughts as <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> who was a burning and a ſhining candle.<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.35</note> Indeede good patients you anſwere well for your Phyſitions, <hi>propter hoc Ly.</hi> But there is great oddes in theſe lights: <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> was to the Church as the candle in the womans hand, to helpe her to finde her loſt groat: and the Ieſuites are as the fier which came out of the bramble,<note place="margin">Graeta fide vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantes. <hi>Eſay 9.16</hi>
               </note> to conſume the Cedars of Lebanon. Yea thoſe <hi>mount-backes of Rome,</hi> put out many eies, and giue ſight to none, <hi>ignes fatui,</hi> they walke wilde in the darke, blind-fold their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, miſleade them out of the true way, and are too often as wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier, but touch and take.<note place="margin">Iud. 15.5</note> We reade of Foxes tied by the tailes with fier-brands, and ſent into the corne fields to deſtroy them. It might haue bin ſaid of England,<note place="margin">Iohn 4.35</note> look on the regions how all the field is white vnto
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20345:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>harueſt. But out of queſtion, our field is not ſo pleaſant as it was, for the Foxes fier which hath waſted much corne. They are but tied by the tailes, and ſo they runne into Ladies chambers; it were good that they were tied by the neckes, and laid to ſleepe in the middeſt of their own fier-brands.</p>
            <p>But ſhall I turne my thoughts from theſe witch-blaſts, to the Roſe of England, all ſweet loue to his Sauiour, all, and all inuiolable loue to his ſauing word. No flatterer hath ſeduced him, no craft hath ſnared him, no canker-worme hath waſted him. Who ſhould not loue the ſmell of this Roſe?</p>
            <p>The Prince hath a Lillie chaſtitie, in his faith a faire Lillie, growing on a golden pillar, the pillar of honour, the honour of the Temple, the Temple of God: him that ouercommeth I will make a pillar in the Temple of my God. Looke all on this Onichinus, this peercleſſe Preatle, alwaies claſped in white belts, faire ſiluer girdles,; the chaſtity of his minde, body, geſture, conuerſation, with the aſpect of his eies,<note place="margin">Prou 22.11</note> and the grace of his lippes. This is he which loueth pureneſſe of heart, and for the grace of his lippes the King ſhall be his friend. Wee reade of the Lilly that which we know, that it beareth <hi>aureum ſemen</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the flowers: the golden ſeede is ſanctitie <hi>the ſeede fell in good ground and hath brought foorth an hundred folde.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 8. Oſe 7. Oſe 10.12</note> Many other haue ſowen the wind and reaped the whirle-wind, but hee hath ſowen to himſelfe in righteouſneſſe, and reaped after the meaſure of mercy.</p>
            <p>Let euery true heart here, call his ſoule to praier. The Lord grant when that time may happely come, that his ſpouſe ſhall bee choſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the honourable women, that then the Kings daughter may be brought to him, with ioy and with gladneſſe enter into the Kings pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace. So ſhall wee then reioice, and againe I ſay reioice in the ſmell of this Lillie.</p>
            <p>The Prince hath the Violet humility, in his faith an elect valley all of beautifull proſpect; ſo high a Prince, ſo lowly in his ſeruice to think ſo highly of God, and ſo truly of himſelfe: <hi>Aquae deſcendunt ad val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> God giueth grace to the humble, to bee frequent at praiers, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, holy quiers; as if his cheefe deſire were as <hi>Dauids</hi> was, to dwell in the courts of the Lord; to bee a friend to the Church, and a ſtay to the Altar, as good <hi>Ioſiah</hi> was.<note place="margin">4 Reg. 23</note> 
               <hi>Quanto magis arbor abundat fructibus tanto magis inclinatur:</hi> more any tree doth abound with fruite, more doth it bend it ſelfe to their commodity who are vnder it. Thus doth he increaſe in fauour with God and man: <hi>Charilaus</hi> the peoples ioy, all his garments ſmell of the Sanctuary; his fathers ioy, as <hi>Iacob</hi> was to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20345:16"/>
               <hi>Iſaac.</hi> Who doth not ioy in the ſmell of this Violet.</p>
            <p>The Prince hath the Corne-care, holy workes in his faith, as if hee had digeſted that counſell of the wiſe-man. <hi>All that thine hand ſhall finde to doe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 9.8.10</note> 
               <hi>doe it with all thy power, for there is neither worke, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, nor knowledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S.</hi> Auguſtine.</note> 
               <hi>nor wiſdome in the graue. Qui vult ſine fine remunerari, debet ſine fine bonum operari,</hi> hee which would haue end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe reward,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.15</note> muſt haue endleſſe perſeuerance: for ſo is the will of God, that by well doing you put to ſilence the ignorance of the fooliſh men;<note place="margin">Iob. 29</note> as <hi>Iob</hi> did, who continued an e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to the blind, and a foot to the lame. If any enemie thinke heere, hee can ſmell <hi>oleum peccatoris,</hi> I profeſſe to hate it <hi>ſplendiduml, ubricum, dulce, damnoſum:</hi> as yee for ſlipping, and the cup of a whore for poiſoning. And I dare bee bold to giue in an inſtance for mine owne defence, that of al others we poor deſpiſed Miniſters haue cauſe to bleſſe the daies of the Prince. Why ſo? for Chriſt his Mandrakes haue ſweetned his; and his Mandrakes haue ſweetned ours. O heauenly Mandrakes, graces of the ſpirit, which diſpoſe to the conception of good workes. The Church is <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaile,</hi> her fathers ioy, and Chriſt hath lodged with her; the Prince is a ſonne and heire in the Church, and Chriſt hath lodged with him by ſpiration of his holy word, by inſpiration of his holy Spirit; that the Prince may ſay,<note place="margin">Cant. 5.4</note> as the Church hath ſaid: <hi>My bowels were mnooued towards him.</hi> Heere is our true cauſe of ioy without ſophiſtically op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilations. Therefore ſeeing his inclination to good workes by thoſe ſpices of our Sauiour, which haue ſpiced him; wee all conſent in that concent of the Canticle of Chriſt:<note place="margin">Cant. 7.13</note> 
               <hi>Thy Mandrakes haue giuen a ſmell, and in our gates are all ſweet things.</hi> The Princes words are often as the words of the ſeuenth day; words of grace, apples of gold in pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of ſiluer;<note place="margin">Prou. 2.11 Leu. 25</note> his works are as the works of the ſeuenth yere, works of grace; a goodly tree, full of fruites. You may know the tree by the fruites,<note place="margin">Apoc. 2</note> and praiſe the fruites for the ſmell. This ſmell is as Smirna, all ſweet myrrhe; and wee all are refreſhed with the ſmell of this Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care.</p>
            <p>Now then let vs compare <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> Hebrew and Engliſh; <hi>vte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinos fratres,</hi> two twins both in one womb of the Church, both as <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 28.11.</note> the badge of our Ship. <hi>Caſtor</hi> is deſcended, and as the Sun gone vnder a cloud: he was gathered to his people, and is gone to ſleep with his fathers.<note place="margin">Gen. 49.33</note> What then? albeit he ſleep he is aliue, &amp; ſhall riſe againe as the Sun in his faire horizon.<note place="margin">Exod. 3.6</note> God is the God of the liuing, the God of <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Iſaac,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iaacob:</hi> But I ſay <hi>Caſtor</hi> is layd down in peace and <hi>Pollux</hi> is vpon our Ship in daily aduentures for the golden flece.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20345:16"/>When I was of younger yeares,<note place="margin">Apollonius Theocritus.</note> I did reade of the famous Acts of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> in that egregious voyage for the Golden Fleece. But what idle dreames were thoſe, with all their reſolutions, to the high reſolutions of religious hearts, for the golden fleece, the fleece of the Lambe, the Lambe of God, the inualuable righteouſneſſe of the Lambe of God is the golden fleece.<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> are both naked as <hi>Adam,</hi> before the Lord, without this fleece. Conſider the ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the honour and efficacie of this fleece,<note place="margin">Rom. 4. Pſal. 32.</note> wherewith all our ſins are couered. Many, many thouſands haue yeelded vp their blood, for this fleece: <hi>hoc expeditionum Chriſtianarum praetium &amp; praemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um:</hi> This hath beene the faire paiment for many Chriſtian aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>The holy lambe alloweth vs his fleſh to feed vs,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.1. Tim. 6.8.</note> his fleece to couer vs. Therefore when we haue food and raiment, let vs be therewith content. Such was <hi>Iacobs</hi> contentment in his new coate, when he got the bleſſing in his elder brothers coate. Chriſt is our elder brother, our firſt borne, a ſonne to <hi>Iacob,</hi> yet elder then <hi>Iacobs</hi> grandfather: <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Abraham was I am.</hi> A lambe without ſpot was this Lambe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8</note> yet that he might lend his ſpotleſſe coate to ſpotted <hi>Iacob,</hi> hee was ſlaine, from the beginning of the world.<note place="margin">Apoc. 13.8.</note> Behold then a world of wonders in theſe two, <hi>Iacob</hi> the elder and the younger, notwithſtanding ſundry generations betwixt them, doe both part ſtakes in Chriſt; either of them haue all their riches of Chriſt, yet neither of them haue all which is of Chriſt: either of them haue all Chriſt, for Chriſt is not diuided;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. Rom. 11.</note> neither of them haue all that which is Chriſts, for Chriſt is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended. Chriſt is the Owner of all in the ſhippe, and of the ſhippe and all, and they both are but partie borrowers of all their parts. So that <hi>Iacob</hi> aboue with Chriſt in glorie, and <hi>Iacob</hi> below with Chriſt in grace, may both ſing with that ſweet ſinger of Iſrael,<note place="margin">Pſal. 142.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is my portion in the land of the liuing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now let vs ſee the diſtance of perfection betwixt Chriſt &amp; theſe two brothers: <hi>Iacob</hi> hath the vine, and Chriſt is the vine; <hi>Iacob</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth all thoſe pleaſant riches in Chriſt, and Chriſt poſſeſſeth them all himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is the vine, the true vine, which runnes all mercie and life to <hi>Iacob,</hi> and all wither and periſh which doe not abide in this vine.<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt is the Oliue, the true Oliue ſtocke, what branch ſoeuer abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not in him, hath no life in it; for the branches beare not the roote,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.18.</note> but the root the branches: all fade and fall away which are not grafted into this Oliue.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:20345:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Chriſt is the roſe,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.</note> of all flowers the roſe is cheefeſt, and of all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues loue; the chiefeſt of thoſe three is loue: God is loue, and he that dwelleth in him dwelleth in loue: out of this habitation there is no health nor ſafetie.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is the Lillie,<note place="margin">Cant. 2. <hi>Jſidor.</hi>
               </note> the moſt delightfull Lillie; for he which is the Roſe is the Lillie: <hi>I am the Roſe and the Lillie of the field: Multiplicis medicinae,</hi> to open dangerous paſſages, to ſoften hardneſſe of heart, to heale wounds,<note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> and repell venemous infections. O conſider this Lillie of the field, for our chiefeſt comforts are in this Lillie.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is the Violet,<note place="margin">Matth. 11.</note> the ſweeteſt Violet, which groweth lowe by the ground: <hi>Learne of me, for I my ſelfe am mecke and lowely.</hi> This vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let was remoued from heauen to the earth, to raiſe vs from the earth to heauen. Some Philoſophers hold opinion, that the dew which fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth from the higheſt part of that Region of the aire, worketh deepeſt vpon the earth; for being more oylie and rich matter, it doth more fatten the ground, and with gentle kiſſes entice forth the fruites there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Hoſoeuer this be of that dew, it is moſt ſure of the fatteſt dewe le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. This is the dew of the morning, which commeth from the higheſt, and falleth loweſt, euen into the center, into the heart of <hi>Iacob.</hi> The dew of heauen is the cauſe of the fatneſſe of the earth, elſe hath the earth no fatneſſe: <hi>ideſt,</hi> the diuinitie of Chriſt is the fatneſſe of our humanitie. <hi>The Lord giue thee of the dew of heauen, and the fatneſſe of the earth.</hi> Here, here, is mans bleſſed abundance. This is Manna,<note place="margin">Exod. 16.</note> ſweet Manna, the bread of Angels, all about the Church, as the dew lay round about the hoſt; ſweet dew, ſweet as the violet, and the ſmell of life was in it. Chriſt his humilitie is our glorie, and his loweſt ſteppe to death, was our high ſtaire to life. Yea, in his humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie we are exalted,<note place="margin">Eſa. 53.</note> as with his ſtripes we are healed. <hi>Behold the ſmell of this violet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But laſt of all,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> Chriſt is the corne eare, the right wheat corne which dieth and liueth againe:<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.18.</note> of it ſelfe it dieth and liueth againe. <hi>I haue power to lay downe my life, and to take it vp againe, and all other liue by this.</hi> The ſpirit of grace and the holy Scriptures are the flower of this wheat. The diſciples of Chriſt gathered eares of corne on the ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, and we here in England euery Sabbath day, trauaile through the corne field:<note place="margin">Jn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erlin. Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertus.</note> 
               <hi>Spicae Scripturarum Spiritum viuificantem habent:</hi> Sentences of Scripture haue the ſpirit of life in them. Is any man hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie and can forbeare gathering? <hi>Ambulant per Sata cum Domino qui in Scripturarum meditatione delectantur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rabanus.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They keepe the Lord company in his corne field, which walke on in holy meditations of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20345:17"/>the Scriptures. Ieſus went on the Sabbath day through the corne, and his Diſciples were hungrie, and began to plucke the eares of corne, and rubbe them in their hands, and to eate; common walkers ſometimes plucke and rubbe, but eate not. Theſe feele no neceſſitie of eating, elſe would they eate for hunger, as the Diſciples did. If we be Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, we are farre ſhort of our ſelues, to care onely for neceſſaries to the body, as the Ant or Mouſe make their prouiſion, not caring if the ſoule pine and periſh for want of Sabbath daies co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne. What ſhall we ſay then to the contentious oppoſitions of proud ſpirits, againſt the neceſſitie of ſuch ſuſtenance? The Papiſts themſelues, ſome of them will ſay, that the word of God, either read or preached, doth clenſe the vncleane, enlighten the blind, heale the broken, and raiſe the dead. Yea ſometimes ouercome with the power of the word of God, they will confeſſe a matter of truth,<note place="margin">Rodolph. Franciſ.</note> 
               <hi>Verbum Dei maioris efficaciae quàm medicinae vel reliquiae ſanctorum:</hi> The word of God is the ſicke mans falue, more effectuall then all the drugges of Traditions. Wherefore thinke you, did the Prophet <hi>Eſaie</hi> deliuer from God that Sermon of the excellent abilitie of the word of God, That as raine and ſnowe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the earth to bring forth the budde,<note place="margin">Eſa. 55.</note> that it may giue ſeed to the Sower, and bread to him that eateth: thus the word of God ſhould hearten and releeue the needie.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.16.</note> Wherefore did the Apoſtle ſo much preferre ſpirituall riches before carnall, and pronuounce a woe againſt himſelfe, if he did not preach the Goſpel, to miniſter the bread of life to the Church. The Lord had commanded him to this ſeruice, and therefore he knew he ſhould be beaten with many ſtripes,<note place="margin">Luc. 12.47.</note> if hee did the worke of the Lord negligently. <hi>Ad hoc Apoſtolus tenetur &amp; quod debuit fecit etiamſi non potuit quantum debuit:</hi> The Apoſtle being bound by Gods precept to his office, hee ought to doe as much as hee could, albeit he could not as much as hee ought. A learned man cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth this diſpenſation, <hi>Neceſſitas debiti &amp; iuſtitiae.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caietane.</note> It is indeed of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and dutie to diſtribute the childrens bread to whom it is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And this is the cauſe why it is called <hi>Neceſſitie of obligation, &amp; releefe:</hi> of obligation, in reſpect of Gods commandement: of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, in lew of the peoples want. Thus to this purpoſe was it ſaid, That the miniſter may euer find cauſes too many, to cauſe him to worke <hi>propter populi indigentiam,</hi> where is more neede to beſtow more feed. This is the corne which we all neede, for a remedie againſt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,<note place="margin">Gregorie.</note> or errour, or ſinne, or any vnbeleefe: therefore come all and taſte, and ſmell how ſweet the Lord is, what varieties of recreations are in the ſmell of this corne eare.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:20345:18"/>
            <p> Sithence then it is euident, that there are ſuch ſtore of gentle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments in our bleſſed Sauiour, that he is all in all, the vine, oliue, roſe, lillie, violet, and corne eare, I would begge an Office to bidde a feaſt.<note place="margin">Prou. 9.</note> Let me this once take vpon me, to inuite gueſts for wiſedom. Whoſoeuer is ſimple, let him come hither, yea whoſoeuer is wiſe, let him come hither. The King, Queene, Prince, and all the royall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genie, the Nobles, Counſellors, Iudges, Rulers, Teachers, and all come taſte,<note place="margin">O dor Chriſti eſt Spiritus ſempiternè recreatiuus.</note> and feele, and ſmell the kindneſſe of the Lord. He is all word of eternall life: here is our feeding, he is all mercie, and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes: here is our healing, he is all fulneſſe of grace, here is our ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. He is ſweet in ſpeaking, ſweet in ſmelling: ſweet in ſpeaking, neuer man ſpake like this man:<note place="margin">John 7.46.</note> ſweet in ſmelling, all merits and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of ſuſtentation, preſeruation, and of ſaluation. O bleſſe Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, in the ſauour of thy oyntments we will runne after thee, that we may be as the King,<note place="margin">Cant. 1.</note> and the Kings ſonne, ſweet in thy ſweetneſſe. Thus we praiſe and bleſſe the ſmell of the Kings ſonne, and paſſe here the firſt riuer of Paradiſe, all of the ſweet ſmell of mercie. Mercies of God to the King, in his gift of this ſonne: mercies of God to this ſonne, in the gifts of his graces: and mercies of God to vs all, in both theſe gifts; of the King, and the Kings ſonne: <hi>Behold the ſmell of my ſonne.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:20345:18"/>
            <head>THE SECOND SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>GEN. 27.27.</bibl>
                  <p>Behold, the ſmell of my ſonne is as the ſmell of a field, which the Lord hath bleſſed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am returned to remeditate our ioies in the manifold cauſes of our many ioies. The ſonne to whom I am next now in my text, doth diſplay many ioies; all cauſes of ioy to vs, all, if we all as birds of the day, be in loue with this ſonne.</p>
            <p>Now to the ſecond riuer all of truth. <hi>My Sonne.</hi> Heere I might deale forth vnto you many multiplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſonnes of nature, grace, and glory, but heere <hi>Laconiſmus</hi> is beſt welcome. There is a ſonne of nature, and a ſonne of grace, which both haue intereſt in this riuer of the truth of God: One as the owner and Lord Pooramont, the other as tenant and inholder. The ſonne of God by nature, is Ieſus Chriſt the truth it ſelfe, and God of truth, the ſonne of diuine generation, the onely begotten ſonne of God,<note place="margin">Symbolum Nic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Iohn 3.</hi>
               </note> begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before all worlds. There is a ſonne of grace, the ſonne of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, borne againe of the ſpirit of God, borne vnto glory in the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall Ieruſalem among the company of innumerable Angels.<note place="margin">Hebr. 12.22</note> Such a ſonne is <hi>Iaacob,</hi> a pleaſant ſonbne by the holy participation of the communicable graces of the naturall ſonne of God. Heere may wee take a ioyfull view of our releaſe from the poſt-fines of ſinne, both feare and ſhame.<note place="margin">Frigius.</note> The ſuperbious Stagge cannot but feare the little Dogge. Why ſo? becauſe he is but nature: And albeit hee be proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in compariſon, and beareth ſtrong armes vpon his head, yet doth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20345:19"/>he fly with ſhame. The true Iſraelite albeit hee be but a yongue ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and the leaſt of all his brethren as <hi>Dauid</hi> was, yet he cannot feare the roring Lion. Why ſo? becauſe he hath grace, a priuilege aboue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Why,<note place="margin">Iohn 17.12</note> what is <hi>Iacob</hi> by nature? a ſonne of the earth, of fleſh, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, death, wrath, hell and perdition.</p>
            <p>I might ſhew you all theſe fleſh-brands in mine owne nature to my ſhame; but my ſhort time cals for better matter. What mends hath grace made? behold, how good and ioyfull a thing it is: <hi>Iaacob</hi> is a ſonne of heauen, earth aboliſhed; a ſonne of the ſpirit, fleſh morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; a ſonne of light, darkneſſe vaniſhed; a ſonne of delight, wrath abandoned;<note place="margin">Mat. 9.15 1. Cor. 15.</note> a ſonne of life, death is ſwallowed vp in victory; a ſonne of the bride groomes chamber, death is ſwallowed vp in victory, and all diſhonour is exiled for euer more. Such ſonnes are <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> Hebrew and Engliſh, King <hi>Salomons</hi> loue betwixt them. King <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> made himſelfe a Pallace of the trees of Lebanon,<note place="margin">Cant. 3.9</note> all white and ſweet as Frankinceſe of Lebanon. Theſe two are trees of Lebanon, <hi>Suauitate &amp; candore morum melliti, eburnei, ſaccarati &amp; lactei;</hi> ſweet and white as the trees of Lebanon. Loe here is the ſmell of my ſonne. <hi>What is it thinke you, a ſmall matter to become the Kings ſon? Iaacob</hi> is <hi>Iſaacs</hi> ſonne, and the Prince is the Kings ſonne, and they all are Gods ſonnes,<note place="margin">Eph. 1.14</note> elected, adopted, ſanctified, iuſtified, and ſealed, vnto the day of redemption. Thus are they all made wiſe ſonnes: a wiſe ſonne maketh a glad father: and hee that begetteth a wiſe ſonne ſhall haue ioy of him:<note place="margin">Prou. 10 Prou. 13</note> as happely the King hath of the ſmell of his ſonne.</p>
            <p>Shall I now begge a diſcourſe?</p>
            <p>There haue beene euill ſonnes of euill fathers, as the ſonnes of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Cham:</hi> euill ſonnes of good fathers, as ſome ſonnes of <hi>Dauid:</hi> good ſonnes of euill fathers, as <hi>Ezechiah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Achah,</hi> and <hi>Ioſiah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ammon:</hi> and good ſonnes of good fathers, ſuch were <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iaacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt ſort were a iuſt recompence that they ſhould bee ſerued themſelues as they had ſerued others. The ſecond ſort were vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full birds which ſtained their owne neſt,<note place="margin">Iuda. 5 1. Sam. 2 17</note> and cauſed their fathers to ſmell ill before the vncircumciſed, as <hi>Hely</hi> his ſonnes did. He might iuſtly complaine againſt his ſonnes, as the Iewes did iniuſtly againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 5.21</note> yee haue cauſe our ſauour to bee lothſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> The third ſort were a bleſſed allowance, theſe ſnined as light in the middeſt of a crooked generation,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.15</note> their fathers before and their ſonnes after, beeing ſet vpon euill. But the fourth ſort is the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20345:19"/>honour and ſplendor of the Church;<note place="margin">Firmamentu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> veritatu in Chriſto confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum. <hi>Apoc. 5.8 Prou. 27.9</hi>
               </note> good ſonnes of good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, all in the Church, as the lights in the firmament. All theſe are as the golden Viols full of odors, odoriferous and delectable to their parents, as ointment and perfume reioice the heart. You Nobles, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, Merchants, and Fathers all, what are your ſonnes? euill of euill, or euill of good, or good of euill, or good ſonnes of good fathers, which is more to bee deſired then gold. Trie the ſmell of your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and prooue whether your ſonnes and daughters haue beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate to diuels, as many were among the children of Iſrael.<note place="margin">4 Reg. 17.17</note> By euill example many giue their children to the ſorcerie of Popery, and to all prophaneſſe of opinion and malefaction. Through fier they paſſe to Prieſts and Ieſuites, to the orders and diſorders of Rome.<note place="margin">Ad bullatas nug as magu aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> piciunt quam ad ſcripturas vt Aſint ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina malunt quam aurum.</note> Many of your children are ſent to <hi>Lypſius</hi> his Ladies to ſeruice, and to the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natian Friars to ſchoole. The ſonnes of the Prophets were diſcriples and ſchollers of the Prophets, ſonnes of good ſmell: many of yours are <hi>ali enigenae,</hi> cuckoo birds, ſtrangers to your owne country Church and Prophets, and liuing ſometimes euen in the middeſt of all, loue not the heart of any. The King is the head here in his dominions next vnder God, and the Prince is the heart vnder the head: your children loue neither of them, no nor their parents neither, but to ſerue their owne turne, and their great Miſtris the <hi>Whore of Babylon.</hi> You may too many of you thanke your ſelues, you haue yeelded them to their courſe (as <hi>Daedalus</hi> did his ſonne in the fiction) with wax vpon their wings, <hi>bullis indulgentialibus linitas.</hi>
               <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nc p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtinaci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> papiſtica vt Eutichiana, in hac fide geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſum etiam vſque hodie vixi et in ea opto mori.</note> Too many of you haue ſet them in tune, or rather out of tune, to your owne Romane inſtruments, your hearts. Thus your corrupt children are gone backward, they are ſtrangers from the wombe, euen from the belly haue they erred and ſpeake lies, <hi>Mandrabuli more,</hi> worſe and worſe. If you thinke this reaſon giuen of your ſonnes ruines be without reaſon, hearken to the Prophet. <hi>Thy father was an Ammorite, and thy mother an Hittite, and in thy natiuity, when thou waſt borne, thy nauell was not cut,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vt è ſinubus nubium e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantur fulmina et tonitrua, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus coloni in aruis affligun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ita è co, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus malorum parentum euol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uuntur pſſimi filij ſuis vicini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cruente infeſti.</note> 
               <hi>nor wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, nor ſaulted, &amp;c.</hi> Good tutors and teachers ſhould performe the offices of good mid-wifes to your children; theſe to helpe them in their generation, thoſe to further them in their regeneration.</p>
            <p>This is the cauſe that there are among vs ſo many young Amorites and Hittites for want of holy education. Amorites and Hittites a bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter people, cruell rebels, yet pratlers, which dare ſo vaunt themſelues, that they are euen an aſtoniſhement vnto vs.</p>
            <p>But may I bee ſo bold heere, to aske another queſtion. What are ſuch parents better then <hi>Tantalus, Cambyſes,</hi> or <hi>Lyſimachus.</hi> One of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20345:20"/>them killed his ſonne of pride, another of furie, and the third of foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh loue. The popiſh father is right as <hi>Lyſimachus,</hi> who by the curſed perſwaſion of a cruell ſtep-mother killed his ſonne, his valiant ſonne <hi>Agathocles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Haud ero ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, dum ſit ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi tanta ſecuris</note> 
               <hi>O Nouerca Roma,</hi> thou haſt intiſed many a father to murder his owne child, and many children to reuolt from God a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hearted father,<note place="margin">Papa caput eſt eccleſiae, vt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus eſt Domi in ſe fumos Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiticos recipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, et effundens vt enecet. <hi>Ier 39.3 Apoc. 18 Deut. 13 Deut. 18</hi>
               </note> and the true Church a moſt louing mother. Yes by thy inſtigations as the ſtings of the Hornet, thou haſt ſet to worke many a <hi>Ragmag</hi> and <hi>Neregall.</hi> Theſe as a cloſe couered candle haue ſecretly kindled fire vpon chriſtian States, to melt and diſſolue all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gouernment. Ah, thou haſt imployed <hi>Ragmag</hi> and <hi>Neregall,</hi> with all the reſt of the Princes of the King of Babell, to teare off the life, or religion, or peace, or all, from Ieruſalem. <hi>O Nouerca Roma,</hi> Queene mother, thou ſaieſt thou art a Queene, but thou art a dreamer, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuer, a charmer, a regarder of times, a counſellour with euill ſpirits, a ſtep-mother, as thoſe <hi>Lurida terribiles miſcent aconita Nouercae,</hi> alwaies tampring with poyſon for Gods children.<note place="margin">Menander.</note> Did not the Poet dreame of thee in thoſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. There is not a worſe miſchiefe then a wicked ſtep-mother.<note place="margin">Per ea quae ſunt placida ſuade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t foeda. <hi>3 Reg. 18.4 4 Reg. 11.1</hi> Quae dedit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidus mella ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nena puto.</note> Let thy ſiſters, either <hi>Phaedra</hi> or <hi>Medea</hi> be thy Iudges, how thou haſt raged againſt Kings children: or thinke of them of whom thou art more certaine in holie writte, how thy ſiſters <hi>Ieſabel</hi> and <hi>Athaliah</hi> ſhall riſe againſt hee in the great day, for killing the Prophets and the Kings linage. Thus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the mild French King before, thus followed the puifant French King after, and both died of their mothers knife. If then the ſunne haue reueiled this way of a Serpent vnder a ſtone: is not Rome <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſharſheol</hi> a Wolfes houſe,<note place="margin">Vbi caſcus caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam duxit.</note> and your good mother a bloud-ſucker? You tell vs daily that your father is holy, his name is holineſſe; but your mother is a murtherer,<note place="margin">De Papa quam plurims quod de hircoſis dicunt, quo redolentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus ſeſe odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramentis fumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gauerint eo te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius olent hyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. Ita pater iſte mendax quo ſacratioris titul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> laruam iudueril eo gra uiorem expirat mephitim eius fallacitas.</note> and therefore we thinke your fathers ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is to blame. The Diuell hath a wide circle compaſſing the earth, and that Strix of Rome is angry as the Bore, which whets his teech becauſe his circuit is not as large as the Diuels. Who ſeeth not alſo, that Satan and his holineſſe are agreed to marke all with their blacke cole, and brand them for Heretikes which bleſſe themſelues with Gods bleſſing out of their reach. Therefore to requite the Popes kindneſſe, I dare preſume to take a little more roome to wraſtle one fall with his holineſſe, for the wrong done to this name of holineſſe. I know well that the Popes ſolliciters haue much confidence in their Champion as the Philiſtines had in <hi>Goliah;</hi> yet muſt hee needes fall which will ſtand on his tiptoes, vaunting himſelfe againſt Gods cauſe as hee did, and more blaſphemous then <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> arrogate
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20345:20"/>to himſelfe the Title which is proper to God.</p>
            <p>This name of God, the type of his incomparable perfection,<note place="margin">Exod. 28.</note> was engrauen onely in gold, the golden letters beeing as the letters of a ſeale, to ſignifie him, who onely by himſelfe, is of himſelfe. It was his proper name, which being holineſſe it ſelfe, is able to make others ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. God is more able to make <hi>Aaron</hi> holy, then fire is able to make the mettall hot, or the ſunne able to infuſe his heat into the day: both theſe creatures may be reſtrained by God, but the Creator by none. God can with hold the naturall powers from the ſtrongeſt,<note place="margin">Exod. 3. Iob. 40.4.</note> and the faireſt; ſo that the fire ſhall not burne in the buſh, nor the ſunne ſhine in Egypt. God can illuminate man with the light of life, and none can forbid it. Canſt thou reſtraine the ſweet influence of the Pleiades, or looſe the bands of <hi>Orion?</hi> hath man an arme like God? Shall then challenge of equalitie with God, in his matchleſſe name, be made by a weake and ſinnefull man, whoſe foundation is duſt, and his daies vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Some of the learned thinke it was the ineffable name of God, which was engrauen on the plate of gold; and ſo they write of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of ſome of the Rabbines, which being granted, then the name there written cannot bee the Popes. What if <hi>Aaron</hi> did beare this name in the Myter vpon his fore-head, yet was it borne not as <hi>Aarons</hi> owne name, but his Maſter his name, whom <hi>Aaron</hi> ſerued, as it is written, <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord.</hi> Let mee yeeld as much vantage as a wraſtler may, and lend the Pope that hold of an ancient father,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Hierom.</hi> Exod. 28.38.</note> 
               <hi>Totam Pontificis pulchritudinem Dei vocabulum coronet &amp; protegat:</hi> But why ſo? <hi>that Aaron may beare the iniquitie of the offerings, &amp;c.</hi> This is plaine which was in ſpeciall commanded for <hi>Aaron,</hi> and none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wherein he was the ſingular type of Chriſt, and of none other; who onely could take away the ſinnes of the world, and none other,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1: 2. Cor. 5.18. <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note> to reconcile the people to God. <hi>We poore Miniſters haue the miniſterie of reconciliation giuen vnto vs, but none are reconciled to God, but by Ieſus Chriſt, for God was in Chriſt, &amp; reconciled the world to himſelfe.</hi> And he which hath the higheſt place in the miniſtration, muſt be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but he cannot be Holineſſe: he muſt be true, but he cannot be the Truth; theſe are Gods preheminences. Therefore is this name Gods onely, and properly, <hi>Quarto modo,</hi> to ſignifie that ſoueraigntie which is aboue the Popes capacitie. But what needeth this attempt (will ſome ſay) to caſt him downe, who hath ſo often <hi>caſt himſelfe downe,</hi> like a blinde man, who cannot ſee, or a drunken man which cannot ſtand?</p>
            <p>How many of the Popes haue beene, as the beaſt, for want of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20345:21"/>light,<note place="margin">Narthecophori multi, Baccbi vero pauci.</note> wanting eles, among the infidels, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did amidſt the Philiſtims, hauing their cogitations darkened, and being ſtrangers from the life of God. Therefore Papacie was called the kingdome of the beaſt. Loe, where is his holineſſe?</p>
            <p>How many of the Popes haue beene luxurious, with carnall and ſpirituall fornication, that thouſands haue walked that way in the twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to the harlots houſe.<note place="margin">Prou. 7.19.</note> You may well thinke that warning peece doth reach to them. How ſhould I ſpare them for this? <hi>Thy children haue forſaken me, and ſworne by them which are no gods: though I fedde them to the full,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier 5.7:</note> 
               <hi>yet they did commit adulterie, and aſſembled themſelues by companies in the harlots houſe.</hi> Therefore was Papacie called the kingdome of the whore. Loe, where is his Holineſſe?</p>
            <p>How many of the Popes haue bin Nicromancers, Coniurers, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanters, Wizards,<note place="margin">Krants.</note> 
               <hi>(quimalis artibus adepti ſunt Pontificatum)</hi> which entered with cruell effuſions of blood, by falſhood, like a Foxe, and paſſing on for a time lyon-like, or like a Tygre, haue at length beene drowned like a dogge in the ſame ſtreame. Their deſpite was great againſt the precept of God: you ſhal not regard inchanters, themſelues being ſuch. There is no ſorcerie in <hi>Iacob,</hi> nor ſoothſaying in Iſrael, much leſſe is <hi>Aaron</hi> a ſorcerer himſelfe. For this ſinne, Papacie was called the Kingdome of the Dragon.<note place="margin">Numb. 23.21.</note> Loe, where is his Holineſſe?</p>
            <p>How many of them haue beene wicked Extortioners, and pillers of many ſtates, which haue ſhifted their hands like Iuglers, with all kinds of beggarly trickes, to ſcrape vp the off all of kingdomes, and to emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie them of prouiſions. Haue not their leane kine eaten vp the fatte, their Monkes, Friers, Seminaries, and Spawne of that monſter <hi>Abad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> haue ſucked <hi>as horſe-leaches,</hi> and deuoured as Locuſts. That Propheſie of <hi>Hildegardis</hi> is worth reading, to make a ſhew of theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, which for their greedie worme, is called the kingdom of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts. Loe, where is his Holineſſe?</p>
            <p>Thus theſe holy Fathers, taking paines to doe euill, by waſting ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, haue ſtriuen for the title. But their ſlight counterſeits are now ſo conſpicuous, that wee dare to ſay, which they dare to prooue, That they haue too many of them, had no more holineſſe then the beaſts loue towards God, the Whore virginity, the Magitian ſincerity, or the Oppreſſor charitie. It is now manifeſt, that all their faire ſhews were but gylden puppies, and your holy Fathers, <hi>Sentinamundi,</hi> the moſt loathſome puddles of all the world. And for further aſſurance, we appeale to the records of thoſe writers, which haue eſpied and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the blots of the Popes, as of common ſtrumpets, &amp; the ſtench
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20345:21"/>of Rome, as the Stewes of Babylon. One ſeemeth to compare hell and Popes together, becauſe neither can be ſatisfied: <hi>Si tibi det ſua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>non repleat tua guttura Craeſus.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe, a better Monke then ordinarie, giueth vs all faire warning: <hi>Si Burſae parcas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob Monach</note> 
               <hi>fuge Papas &amp; Patriarchas:</hi> hee that hath an honeſt care to keepe ſomething, let him flie the Pope and his Proctors, more then any thing. In thoſe dolefull conſiderations of Romiſh impieties, ſome of your owne fauourites haue cried out, that Rome is <hi>Officina fraudum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">F. Petrarch.</note> 
               <hi>clauſtrum irarum nidus proditionum,</hi> commendations not worth Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing: and a bird of your owne feather did flie abroad, crying as a Screech-owle in your owne ſtreetes, <hi>Exeat aula qui vult eſſe pius:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lucan.</note> Let no honeſt man truſt himſelfe in ſuch vnhoneſt company. Loe, where your holineſſe is laid on the ground. May not the Popes fauorites per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ranke ſauor of falſhood, where was (as they thought in their deluded ſenſe) the ſweet ſmell of truth?</p>
            <p>Is not the Popes impudent ambition eaſily eſpied in the vniuſt claime of the Popes vnlawfull title? Heare an ancient ſpeake,<note place="margin">Innoc.</note> 
               <hi>Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſus ſtatim vt eſt ad honorem promotus, in ſuperbiam extollitur, ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantiam effraenatur, non curat prodeſſe, ſed gloriatur praeeſſe: praeſumit ſe meliorem, quia cernit ſe ſuperiorem:</hi> An ambitious man promoted, is blowne about with words, as the Mill-ſaile with winde, all his tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings are more for his owne glory, then common profit. All his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is to carrie all others in his ſtreame:<note place="margin">Virg.</note> 
               <hi>quae rapidus flammis ambit torrentibus amnis.</hi> Albeit pride be the ſinne of falſhood againſt the truth, of <hi>Lucifer</hi> againſt God; yet were it more tollerable, if it were but to ſhew, and not to hurt. Pride loueth the faireſt ſhew: <hi>qua pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrum eſt digito monſtrari, &amp; dicier hic eſt:</hi> It is a faire gloſſe with which the Pope ſhapes his owne coate, that among men, he is as gold aboue all mettalls, and as farre more excellent then Emperour, as Sun aboue Moone: this is the ſunne of the world. If this were all, it were more then enough; but an Heathen telleth vs of a worſe matter:<note place="margin">Seneca.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>Colit hic reges calcet vt omnes:</l>
                  <l>Tantum vt noceat cupit eſſe potens?</l>
               </q> All his loue to Kings, is like his loue to his beſt morſels, that he may deuoure them all, and keepe his foote on their neckes.</p>
            <p>I haue read this queſtion in a Friers Sermon, why there hath beene peace ſo ſeldome in Weſtphalia? The anſwer is, <hi>propter malam conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationem martis plus ibi qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alibi ſe infundentis.</hi> If I might interpret that anſwer, I ſhould deeme the Pope to be <hi>Mars inter planetas, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors</hi> among the Princes. Surely many countries are dangerouſly cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20345:22"/>by the influence of his holineſſe, and haue leſſe reſt by his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominancie in a bloody conſtellation of Cardinals. The ſignes of heauen were appointed for ſeaſons;<note place="margin">Gen. 1.14</note> but this is the ſigne which by force putteth all out of ſeaſon. Where this wandring ſtarre hath rule, there peace may not inhabit in ſafetie. How doth this appeare? Shall I tell you how? <hi>Eliſha</hi> wept at the ſight of <hi>Hazael,</hi> and you would thinke by his name there is no cauſe. <hi>Hazael</hi> is, ſeeing God, as if none ſee God but he; but <hi>Eliſha</hi> wept for the euill he ſhould doe to the children of Iſrael. It is ſaid that <hi>Hazael</hi> was aſhamed when the man of God wept,<note place="margin">4. Reg. 8.12.</note> but he went on with his cruell purpoſes. <hi>O Hazael, his holineſſe is Hazael, ſeeing God, but who can count the euils he hath done,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn de Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſijs.</note> 
               <hi>the ſtrong cities ſet on fire, the young men ſlaine with his ſword, the infants daſhed againſt the ſtones, and women with child rent in peeces.</hi> I might goe further to prooue why this is not incredible, both by the Chronicles of the Popes warres, and by a reaſon without reaſon, that none may puniſh the Pope for any fact. Thus <hi>impunitas auſum parit, auſus exceſſum:</hi> The Pope is as the wild aſſe, which for want of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming doth kicke downe euery burthen. One euill breeds another: but there is too much already in word and deed of this badde matter.</p>
            <p>Now let vs with ioy looke againe on the Kings ſonne, trie his ſpirit hitherto vnvanquiſhed, ſmell the ſweetneſſe of his pretious oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which the Popes dead flies haue not yet corrupted. Fathers, behold the Kings ſonne, and ſee of what faſhion, opinion, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſonnes ſhould be: he ſmels as <hi>Iacob</hi> did, <hi>Iacob</hi> did ſmell of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.1.</note> all of truth. <hi>I muſt confeſſe my ſorrow of heart, in that iuſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, for the faith and truth are diminiſhed from among the children of men.</hi> There are many numbers of them, like idoles of the heathen, which haue eyes and ſee not; or in ſpeciall like <hi>Harpocrates</hi> the dumbe god, which did ſee (as they ſuppoſed) but could not, or would not ſpeake. To all thoſe, whatſoeuer they be, we may truly ſay, <hi>Quid igitur profuit te vidiſſe veritatem quam nec defenſurus es, nec ſecutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus:</hi> As the nice dame which can looke vpon the table richly furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with ſumptuous prouiſions, and hath no ſtomacke to put them vp. It hath beene vrged againſt the Separatiſts long agoe, that the perfection of the Church is aboue, and not belowe, in heauen, and not on earth. And to this purpoſe are inſtances preſſed out of <hi>Pater no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> which was all hands without eies; and <hi>our Father,</hi> which is all eies with out few hands. But ſee here the true proportion of true religion, both hands to doe, and eies to ſee, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Prince, and the Princeſſe, in mutuall armes, embracing and feeding one the other:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20345:22"/>as <hi>Prou.</hi> 8 <hi>Exalt her and ſhe ſhall exalt thee.</hi> This ſonne is <hi>filius dextrae,</hi> the right ſonne royall, the ſonne of the right hand, <hi>compendium gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiarum,</hi> a treaſure of the treaſures of gladneſſe. The eies of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes looke on him, and the nobleſt of all the Nobles ſay of him, thou art worth ten thouſand of one of vs.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.3</note> The true ſonne and true heire to a true King. The ſon, the heire, the title, the inheritance, the creation, all ſauour of truth. <hi>Behold, the ſmell of my ſonne is as the ſmell of a field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heere wee muſt leaue the ſecond riuer, where mercy and truth are mette together in the Prince, as the light and warmth of the ſunne to reioice together as two riuers of Paradiſe to runne one with an other: So that the Prince may happilie ſay in the end;<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.32</note> 
               <hi>I haue runne the way of thy commandements:</hi> and the Lorde may ſay of the Prince; <hi>Behold, the ſmell of my ſonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now are wee come to the cordiall waters of righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>There is among men, a Merchants Righteouſneſſe.</item>
               <item>There is among men, a poore mans Righteouſneſſe.</item>
               <item>There is among men, a proud mans Righteouſneſſe.</item>
               <item>There is among men, a Chriſtians Righteouſneſſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The firſt is the righteouſneſſe of a prophane Merchant, who ſelles all his righteouſneſſe for ſmoke of vaine glory.<note place="margin">Matth. 6.1</note> Take heede of this righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is the righteouſneſſe of a proud Lady, a proud heart in a beggers purſe. Thou ſaieſt, <hi>I am rich and increaſed with goods and haue neede of nothing, and knoweſt not that thou art wretched, and miſerable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 3 Matth. 5.</note> 
               <hi>and poore. But except your righteouſneſſe do exceed the righteouſneſſe of Scribes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third is the righteouſneſſe of the man with a gold ring and goodly apparell, who muſt euer bee the beſt of the company. What hath God commanded which he will not do? This man is as the foole, which hearing that God commanded man to walke ſtreight, neither turning to the right hand nor the left, he would ouer hedge and ditch, hilles and houſes, till hee fell and could paſſe no further.<note place="margin">Eccle. 7.17.18</note> 
               <hi>There is a iuſt man that periſheth in his iuſtice, but be not thou iuſt ouermuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth is <hi>Abrahams</hi> righteouſneſſe. <hi>Hee beleeued and it was counted to him for righteouſneſſe</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So vnderſtand this Scripture that good Chriſtians may put off that ſlander of <hi>Solifidians.</hi> For the true Chriſtan is not fier without heat, or day without light: No, the way of the righteous ſhineth as the light, that ſhineth more and more vnto the perfect day. This is <hi>Iaacobs</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:20345:23"/>righteouſnes gliſtring with his father <hi>Abrahams</hi> righteouſneſſe, both righteous in Chriſt. The ground in which wee find this current of righteouſneſſe is called a field, where wee haue of field roome good ſtore.</p>
            <p>In the word of God we finde diuerſe fields: the field of the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, the field of beaſts,<note place="margin">Prou. 23.10 Pſalm 8.7 Prou. 24</note> and the ſluggards field. In the field of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe the wild Boare doth often roote, and the greedy Wolfe doth make ſubtill entrance. In the field of beaſts <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> liued, all in pride, blaſphemie, rapine, luſt, drunkenneſſe, as too many in our times,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 104</note> liue more like beaſts then men; where all the beaſts of the field doe meete and the wilde Aſſes quench their thirſt. In the ſluggards field are thiſtles and nettles, as a wicked mans life is all full of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue tranſgreſſions, for want of Chriſtian exerciſe. But I haue thought to ſpeake of other fields.<note place="margin">Luke. 6.1 Iohn 18.1</note> There is <hi>ager frumenti,</hi> the corne-field where Chriſt walked: <hi>hortorum,</hi> the field of gardens, where Chriſt praied; the field of bloud &amp; the potters field, bought with the price of bloud; and <hi>ager Meridianus,</hi> the ſun-ſhine field, whither Chriſt is aſcended. This <hi>Meridian</hi> field is the ioyfull Theatre for all true beleeuers, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Iaacob</hi> and <hi>Iaacob</hi> are riſen with Chriſt:<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3</note> the one <hi>ſpe,</hi> the other <hi>re;</hi> one <hi>initians,</hi> the other <hi>initiatus;</hi> one in <hi>via,</hi> the other in <hi>patria;</hi> one in poſſeſſion,<note place="margin">1. Joh. 3.14 Ioh. 5.24.</note> the other in infallible aſſurance: <hi>For we know that we are tranſlated already from death to life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what field is <hi>Iaacob?</hi> a corne-field: ſo haue we heard of him in the corne-eare, that his Corne, and Wine, and Oile increaſed; Faith, Hope,<note place="margin">Cant. 4 16.</note> and Loue. <hi>Iaacob</hi> is a field of gardens, all of <hi>vigent</hi> flowers, and <hi>pinguous</hi> hearbes of grace; that of his owne heart he may ſay with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent deſire: <hi>Let my beloued come into this garden and eate his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant things.</hi> Let come proſperity, aduerſity, or terror, or flattery, or what ill blaſt ſoeuer,<note place="margin">Ionah 4 7. Iob. 1 Cant. 4.16</note> as on <hi>Ionahs</hi> gourd, or <hi>Iobs</hi> houſe, yet this field ſhall proſper, and the more it is blowen, more ſweet it ſmelles. Ariſe O North, and come O South, and blow on my garden, that the ſpices thereof may flow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iacob</hi> is a field of bloud; the vndefiled bloud of the Redeemer was ſprinkled vpon him,<note place="margin">Apoc. 14.1</note> the bloud of the Lambe of God which ſtandeth on mount Sion. The bloud of the Lambe was let out by his enemies in the field of bloud, but it was ſhed vpon his friends, as water on the thirſty ground to comfort it.</p>
            <p>This is the bloud of the Teſtament which God hath appointed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.<note place="margin">Hebr. 9.12</note> Yea this precious bloud was powred out vpon the rich fields of heauen and earth, that we might be all one flocke, bought and paid
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20345:23"/>for, and ſeiſed into poſſeſſion by his precious bloud-ſhedding: <hi>he hath ſet at peace through the bloud of the Croſſe, both things in heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1 20</note> 
               <hi>and things in earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iaacob</hi> is a potters field, Chriſt Ieſus was laid vp in this field,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.7</note> that <hi>Iacob</hi> might die to ſinne and liue to righteouſeneſſe. <hi>Iaacob</hi> hath hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly treaſure in an ear then veſſell:<note place="margin">Matth. 13.4</note> Chriſt is the hidden treaſure in the potters field, more worth then all the field.</p>
            <p>But ſhall I ſay that <hi>Iaacob</hi> is a <hi>Meridian</hi> field? yes a goodly ſun-ſhine field of common ioy, and profit to the Church.</p>
            <p>As the common court of the Tabernacle was vpon the ſun-ſhine ſide, a faire and comely paſſing to the Church:<note place="margin">Exod. 27.9</note> Thus was <hi>Iacob</hi> a faire field of common paſſage for the Saints, for all muſt come by <hi>Iaacob. This is the generation of them which ſeeke him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 24.6</note> 
               <hi>of them which ſeeke thy face O Iaacob. Noſtrum eſt rapere regnum coelorum per gratiam quod quis nequeat attingere per naturam:</hi> our nature being lame,<note place="margin">Ierome. Chriſoſtome.</note> we muſt be ſtrengthened in grace, to hold heauen by violence.</p>
            <p>So then, albeit <hi>Iaacob</hi> be a common field, in whoſe faire paths and ſteppes of faith, we repaire daily towards the houſe of God. Yet is he but a figure of a fairer field; for Chriſt himſelfe is for vs: all our rich faire common field.</p>
            <p>He is <hi>ager frumenti,</hi> where we haue all our bread of life.<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.</note> Hee is <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger hortorum,</hi> where all the Church hath all her ſpices. He is <hi>ager ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis,</hi> our mercy, truth, righteouſneſſe, and peace, beeing all died in his bloud, who did tread the winepreſſe alone. Hee was <hi>ager figuli,</hi> a man of earth, in all things like vnto man ſinne onely excepted: hee bare the ſhape of a ſeruant in our potters field. Yet this was his priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that his veſſell was not broken. Hee was pierced with thornes and ſcourges, and bored through with nailes and ſpeare, but he could not be broken among the ſpoiles of death: Not a bone of him ſhall be broken.<note place="margin">Eſa. 12.46 Eſa. 53.5</note> Hee was broken for our iniquities in the ſeparation betwixt his body and ſoule; but his body could not be corrupt, becauſe it was neuer attaint with ſinne; with which ſeale the ſtay of our field is put together. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſuffer thine holy one to ſee corruption.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 16.10</note> When all his enemies had done againſt him what they could, hee wonne the maſterie from them all, as the ſun at none day doth winne the victory of all the clouds of darkneſſe, and is thus become our Meridian field. Heere ſtands our glorious ſonne the King of glory, as the ſunne in Gibeon on the top of the hil, whileſt the Lord doth fight for Iſrael.<note place="margin">Ioſh. 10 Verſ. 13.14 Apoc. 1</note> The ſunne abideth in the middeſt of our heauen, as the ſon of man in the middeſt of ſeuen golden candleſtickes, and there is no day like this.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20345:24"/>Chriſt Ieſus is our common field,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.24</note> and there is neither Iewe nor Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, nor bond, nor free, ſhut out, which haue any title in this field, as the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt for a wedding garment.<note place="margin">Matt. 22.11</note> There are none ſecluded which making right vſe of their talents haue right de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to enter into the Lords ioy,<note place="margin">Matt. 25.21</note> as the wiſe virgins, which went in with the bridegroome into the wedding. Here we all gather plenteous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, as <hi>Ruth</hi> gathered plentie of releeſe in the field of <hi>Boaz:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth 2.15</note> 
               <hi>Let her gather among the ſheaues, and doe not rebuke her.</hi> O bleſſed <hi>Boaz</hi> our Sauiour, what ſtrength is in thee for vs all? what ſtrong cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity? what faire righteouſneſſe haſt thou ſcattered for vs all to gather? As <hi>Boaz</hi> ſcattered ſome of his ſheaues of ſet purpoſe for <hi>Ruth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 16</note> ſo Chriſt himſelfe let fall ſome of his ſheaues for vs, that we might gather without rebuke.<note place="margin">Eccleſia mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans eſt ſancta imputatione, inchoatione, ſegregatione, ſanctitate multimoda à ſancto ſancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum imbuta.</note> Nay who can tell how many thouſand more Chriſt hath done for vs, that we may gather heauenly fruits, and after feede thereon for euer? It is ſaid of <hi>Ruth</hi> that ſhee gleaned in the field till euening. Heere vntill euening, till the day of this life bee ſpent, wee gather all our good conditions, comforts, profits, pleaſures; all our mercies, ſweet remiſſions, all our truth, true faith, all our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, faire beauty, and all our peace; ſweet reſt vntill our euerlaſting ſabbaths reſt, in that bleſſed field of Gods reſt for euer.</p>
            <p>But all this while where is the Prince? hath hee no place heere, or doth he beare no Armes in this Field? Yes; now let all the worthies of the world looke on him: the Prince is <hi>Hur</hi> all white; cleane hands, and cleane heart, and vpholdeth the armes of his worthy father, as <hi>Hur</hi> did the hands of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to the diſcomfiture of our enemies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he going downe of the ſunne.</p>
            <p>The Prince is a field of Corne,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6 Nom. 24.6 Heb. 10.22. Pſalm. 78.39</note> the Word of God doth plentifully dwell in him. A field of gardens, as the gardens by the riuers ſide. A field of bloud, ſprinkled in his heart from an euill conſcience; and yet a potters field. Let him remember that he is but fleſh, and a winde that turneth not againe.</p>
            <p>What then, are all thoſe ſanctities loſt in him? no, now let my tongue touch my heart, and let my voyce ſhout out for ioy that the Prince is our Engliſh Paradiſe: <hi>Henricus campus meridianus magnae Britanniae:</hi> The Lord ſent him out of the North into the South, and now is he becom our meridian field, for the health and wealth of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome. The Lord hath brought againe the captiuitie of Sion,<note place="margin">Pſalme 126.1</note> and here is the health and wealth of theſe dominions. <hi>Now ſhake thy ſelfe from the duſt, ariſe, and ſit downe O Ieruſalem, looſe the bands of thy necke, O captiue daughter Sion.</hi> Shall I compare with that happie
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20345:24"/>time of our bleſſed Queene <hi>Elizabeth?</hi> They which were baniſhed in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> time for ſowing, were ſent for againe in <hi>Elizabeths</hi> daies to reape: a fauourable recompence of God,<note place="margin">Pſal 126 5</note> that they which did ſowe in teares might reape in ioy. <hi>In former time, the people went downe into Egypt, and Aſhur oppreſſed them without cauſe: but now how beautifull vpon the mountaines are the Watchmen, which ſee, &amp; lift vp their voyce, and ſhout together.</hi> Now is our mouth filled with laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">Verſ. 2</note> and our tongue with ioy, our ioy renewed, new ioy doubled, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ioy multiplied, our manifold ioyes eſtabliſhed in the King, and the Kings ſonne.</p>
            <p>Heere is cauſe enough for vs all to confeſſe the largeſſe of Gods mercifull, true, and righteous dealing, in the performance of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.<note place="margin">Leu. 26.9.</note> 
               <hi>I will haue reſpect vnto you, and make you increaſe, and multiply you, and eſtabliſh my couenant with you.</hi> A moſt happie performance, that now we haue hope for feare, truth for doubt, righteouſneſſe for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice, peace for warre, right heires for wrong, as firre trees for thorns,<note place="margin">Eſay 55.13</note> and mirrhe trees for nettles. Now are our faireſt riuers in the South, the faire ſtreames turned hither in righteouſneſſe, with ioy and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to themſelues, and all iuſt men. <hi>Lord thou haſt turned our capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, as riuers in the South.</hi> How did the ioyes of good ſubiects hearts ſparkle out at their eies, attending to the Kings comming, as the Angel of the Lord, to leade his people. The King came firſt, and his Angel came after, <hi>as the hawke doth flie by thy wiſdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 39.29.</note> 
               <hi>ſtretching out his wings towards the South.</hi> It is written of the South-winde, that his originall is in the North; but when he paſſeth the coaſts of the Zodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acke towards the South, there to meet the ſunne, as the ſole Lord of all thoſe beautifull paſſages, then is he whot and moiſt, and yeeldeth power to all the nurſeries of Nature, to worke, from the worme that creepeth, to the bird which flieth. If I doe not miſtake the likeneſſe, this is a likely preſident of the faire arriuall here of the King, and the Kings ſonne, to the gladneſſe of Nature, and Art, and Grace, and to the common ſolace of poore and rich, both naked wormes, and feathered fowles. Now all true ſubiects, eaſed of all their feares, may ſing vnder their owne vines. <hi>Loe how our clothes are warme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 37.17.</note> 
               <hi>when he maketh the earth quiet, through the South winde.</hi> In what corners are thoſe to be found, which doe not reioyce in this ioy? <hi>Henrie</hi> Prince of Wales is our Meridian field, richly mantled with pleaſant varieties of high ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. His Father <hi>Apollo,</hi> the King, hath watered him, his excellent father, his God, his high father, hath increaſed him in holy infuſions of grace, and rich ornaments of the pureſt Diſcipline. Now is the Prince
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20345:25"/>his Court more ſeemely to behold, then the bankes of the Muſes, all bright and famous, with faire fountaines of knowledge, all garniſhed as a mellifluous garden, where many Bees doe gather hony vnder the Maſter Bee, Lord of the ſoyle: <hi>Behold, the ſmell of my ſonne is as the ſmell of a field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some write of the magnanimous aduentures of the Holy Land,<note place="margin">Mantuan Sotterus. Euſebius Faber.</note> ſome of the ſpatious propagation of the Goſpel, through Ethiopia, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, India, and Grecia, in the time of the Apoſtles: ſome of the wide ſpreading of the triumphant banner of Ieſus Chriſt, in theſe latter times, among the Arabians, Perſians, and Indians: but who can write wherefore God hath giuen ſuch iudgements to the King, and ſuch righteouſneſſe to the Kings ſonne;<note place="margin">Pſal. 72.</note> this were worth the Penne of a ready writer. This wee all ought to doe, to offer vp our <hi>hands, and hearts, and all our aid to the King, and the Kings ſonne.</hi> The Goſpel is yet in bondage in our neighbour countries and ſtates remote, and there is no Prince in the world of more aſſurance for Gods aſſiſtance,<note place="margin">Pſal. 144.1.</note> to teach his hands to warre, and his fingers to fight. There is none more likely to helpe, by the ſmell of his field, all zealous pietie, and reſolute integritie, that euery confident heart may ſay to him, who knoweth whether thou art come to the kingdome for ſuch a time.</p>
            <p>In my weake meditations I haue found, that God hath fowen his diuers kinds of ſeeds in three ſundry fields: in Paradiſe, in the wide World, and in the ſoule of man. In Paradiſe a pure man, in the world a pure word, and in the ſoule of man pure ſeedes of grace. In Paradiſe, the firſt man <hi>Adam</hi> was made a liuing ſoule,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.45.</note> without hang-bies of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall ſinne, or in-bred hoſtilities of ſtrong preuaile. Therefore the complaint of mans fall is two-fold, one againſt mans ſecuritie, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt the Serpents enuie: <hi>whileſt Adam ſlept, the enuious man ſowed tares.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 13.</note> Thus was man corrupt both within and without, in his body, and his ſoule, when the pure <hi>Adam</hi> receiued in the impure ſting of ſinne, as <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> liuing, receiued in his ſleepe his deaths wound.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 4.6.</note> Man did not continue in honour, but became like vnto the beaſts which periſh.<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.12.</note> In the ſecond field, the Lord hath beſtowed his liuely word, of which the great ſower ſaith himſelfe, <hi>For this cauſe was I borne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 18.37. Eſay 1.9. Rom. 9.29.</note> 
               <hi>and for this cauſe came I into the world.</hi> Therefore well may we ſay, <hi>Except the Lord had reſerued ſeed for vs, wee had beene as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and like to Gomorrha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then, among many indifferent queſtions of the Aſtrologers, I reioyce much in this one, to know where is the beſt influence of the heauens. Many men haue many opinions, and if it may pleaſe you to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20345:25"/>accept mine among them all, I thinke the beſt is there where is a moſt plentifull proſemination of the word of God. This is the ſacred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſion, wherewith the moſt parts of our nation is copiouſly ſprinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: <hi>Therefore Iacob ſhall reioyce, and Iſrael ſhall be glad.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 14.7</note> This was the pleaſant meate and drinke, wherewith the King of the Prophets did cheere vp the hearts of his friends, and his owne: <hi>he ſhewed his word vnto Iacob, his ſtatutes and his iudgements vnto Iſrael:</hi> he hath not dealt ſo with euery nation,<note place="margin">Pſa. 147 19, 20</note> all people haue not had ſuch wholeſome influence. This was <hi>Eccleſiae gloria circumfluens &amp; vbertim mala ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pellican.</note> the ſatiable riches of the Church. Thus the mercy and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Lord doth follow vs, hee maketh our cuppe to ouerflowe. Yea, this bleſſed influence filleth innumerable orchards full of figge-trees, Chriſtian conſciences full of the fauours &amp; delights of God. The word of God is a fig tree worth keeping, and tending, where we haue our daily nutriment and comfort,<note place="margin">Prou. 27.8.</note> 
               <hi>For he which keepeth the figge-tree ſhall eate the fruit thereof.</hi> But ſhall I ſpeake what I haue heard from the clamours of the wiſdome of the world, That this great allowance of the word of God, is abundant and ſuperfluous. To ſuch I haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a bold (ſome will ſay a blinde) anſwere. That their wiſedom is the ſooles bable, <hi>which hath ſaid in his heart, There is no God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 14.1.</hi> Excellentia re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giminis Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani non eſt ex opinatione politica, ſed ex ordinatione dominica diri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genda. Jac. de Valen. Aqua nobilis ex frigore ſaepe gelatur.</note> There are too many wiſe men of the Weſt, which hold opinion of common preaching, as ſome Philoſophers doe of the light about the Southerne pole; That as by the abſence of the Sunne there, the aire is not hindred in his light; ſo by the want of ordinary preaching, religion is not darkened in her beautie. <hi>Circa polum Auſtralem, per abſentiam ſolis non defieit lumen conueniens ad vitam felicem.</hi> Indeed ſome to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare much preaching, and too much Sun-ſhine together. <hi>Perpetua aeſtas omnia exurit:</hi> but the danger is more, <hi>ne perpetua hyeme omnia rigerent:</hi> leſt cold religion ſhould be cloſed vp in frozen hearts, and in the want of the warmth of the word of God, this times deuotion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come cold, and dead as ice.</p>
            <p>When I remember this miſcreant conceipt, it ſeemeth to me like a fowle ſerpent, with a great bellie, full of young ones, all deuourers of faith.</p>
            <p>Thus may you more eaſily vnderſtand our Sauiours queſtion, <hi>When the ſonne of man commeth, ſhall he find faith on the earth?</hi> who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, that faith may be ſtarued for want of the waters of comforts, and pined for want of food, and choaked for want of ſpirit: if thou withdraweſt thy breath, then we are gone.<note place="margin">Pſal. 146.4</note> 
               <hi>Thus mans breath depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, he returneth to the earth, and his thoughts periſh.</hi> What then muſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20345:26"/>wee haue nothing but reading of the moſt ſure word of the Prophets,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.19.</note> to take heed vnto? Yes beloued, I would be loth to ſay that we ſhould be acquainted with no other buſineſſe, but reading, expounding, or hearing the word of God; as thoſe Heretickes erred, which would haue nothing but praying.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> I grant there muſt be <hi>Ortus &amp; occaſus Solis,</hi> a time to ſpeake,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.7.</note> and a time to keepe ſilence, a time to ſowe, and a time to mowe. Yet the word of God, as the Sunne, may not be too long downe, leſt there be too much darkeneſſe, and cold ignorance, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition to good manners. And for a parting blowe, to thoſe wiſe men (whoſe wiſdom deſcendeth not from aboue,<note place="margin">Iam. 3.15.</note> but is earthly, ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and deuilliſh) I would commend one anſwer more to them, more to the purpoſe. Their compariſon is not well ioynted, becauſe of the oddes betwixt Nature and Grace.<note place="margin">Pſal. 58.5.</note> The truth is cleare againſt all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which ſtoppe their eares, that albeit there can be too much Sun, (it is pittie that euer faire weather ſhould doe harme) too much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, and blaſts of winde; yet can there neuer be too much faith, loue,<note place="margin">Matth. 8.26.14 31.16.8.</note> obedience, neuer too much grace. Therefore are there ſo many complaints of too little &amp; manifold prayers, that grace may be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied vpon the Church.</p>
            <p>Now muſt I ſpeake of the third field,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1, 2.</note> in which Gods ſeed is ſowen: This field is the ſoule of man,<note place="margin">Ezech. 8.</note> this is Gods field, <hi>All ſoules are mine.</hi> The Lord ſoweth ſeeds of grace purpoſely in our ſoules, that they may growe and out-growe our ſinnes, as ſeeds are ſowen in their ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to out-grow the weeds. <hi>Therefore euery one which is borne of God, doth no ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.4 Pſal. 47.1.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe his ſeed remaineth in him.</hi> Heere then let all Engliſh people clap their hands, &amp; ſing lowd vnto God with a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full voyce, for this one inſtance of a Princely ſoule. In the troupes of many miraculous coniunctions, and oppoſitions, you may all behold ſome ſtrange ones here. Rare coniunctions of Maieſtie and Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, of Youth and Wiſdome, of Temperance and yeares of luſt to ſin. What? <hi>Halcyons</hi> dayes in ſummer? It is reported that the <hi>Halcyon</hi> doth breed in winter, and then there are daies of peace, then warres ceaſe in all the world. In the daies of winter, of old age, then ſinnes ceaſe in <hi>microcoſmo,</hi> the force of carnall deſires are not ſo fierce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſoule: <hi>When the Almond tree ſhall flouriſh, concupiſcence ſhall be driuen away.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.5.</note> But <hi>Halcyons</hi> daies in ſummer, in youth health, ſtrength, and plentie, peace and ſo brietie, in the times of ſtrong rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, inſurrections and skirmage; a paſſing coniunction: This can come to paſſe but onely one way, by which it is thus come to paſſe. The Prince is faſtened to the head,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.19</note> knit with bands and ioynts, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20345:26"/>with the increaſing of God. Without exception this is a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular example of ioyfull aſtoniſhment, as S. <hi>Peters</hi> deliuerance was to be exempt out of the chaines of darkneſſe,<note place="margin">Acts 12.</note> when his friends thought his enemies were too ſtrong againſt him. Is it not a wonder in our daies <hi>(infidelitate epicuriſmis luxuriante ac ſaepius ad atheiſmum vrgente)</hi> yet this incomparable Prince as a pillar of Gods houſe to ſtand faſt, and as a mount that cannot be remoued. There are a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand young plants in the Kingdome ſhaken as reeds, and daily waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, are carried about with euery wind, as clouds without water;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.14 Iude 12.</note> &amp; yet ſtill the Prince groweth as an heauenly plant, which cannot be plucked vp. Looke on him all yee <hi>proſapiae nobiles,</hi> all whoſoeuer ye be of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pedegree, generous progenie, or religious anceſtors, are not his actiue vertues before you ſo many <hi>Heroes,</hi> all ſinging <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Now ſtirre and quit your forces well,<note place="margin">Jſte primus prodijt in Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam vt vos ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quamini.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To cut out ſinne, and caſt downe hell.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And now look on him againe where you may perceiue an oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion like rare, as is the coniunction: <hi>duellum perpetuum,</hi> a moſt martiall combat betwixt opportunitie and ſinne. Theſe two are commonly in league, <hi>alter in alterius iactantes lumina vultus:</hi> ſoothing vp one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as mutuall flatterers. We ſhall ſeldome ſee theſe two to meet at any time without ſhaking of hands as friends; and hardly are they ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if the barres of law be not ſtrong, and of ſound vſe againſt them. Such is the common greeting betwixt them, as betwixt Proſperity and Pride, which are ſeldome perſwaded to part company. There is one greeuous ſorrow with which may parents are painted, that our youth doe beare in their thoughts <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not virgins, but curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſans. Now the leaſt euill word to young men takes fire: youth is, <hi>vt ignis ad torrem,</hi> as haſtie to ſinne as the dry brand to be kindled. There is no need of vnchaſte ſongs and wanton plaies to intice youth to wantonnes, for they are apt to euil, <hi>Et quia facilè vulpes pirum comeſt,</hi> as wiſe to doe wickedly, as the Fox for his prey. Marke then,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plautus.</hi> Luke 16.8.</note> here is an happy marke for you all worth your aime, peareleſſe youth with pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to flie from euill, when as at the ſame yeeres others doe baſely flie to euill. Is not his praiſe and ſtatue iuſtly raiſed, who doth mortifie his vnruly affections, when with ſuch ſtrong enemies, many of the ſtrong young men are ſlaine. Many of the beautifull women &amp; ſtrong men haue periſhed in the power of thoſe enemies, that the Prophet may ſigh and lament; <hi>O that mine head were full of water,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 9.1.</note> 
               <hi>and mine eies a fountaine of teares, that I might weepe day and night for the ſlaine
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20345:27"/>of the daughter of my people.</hi> Verily this young Prince doth with great ioy draw waters out of the welles of ſaluation; that though thouſands fall on his right hand,<note place="margin">Eſay 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.3 Pſal. 91.7</note> and ten thouſand at his left hand, yet the plague cannot come nigh him. Say then this is the faireſt white rocke of all our <hi>Albions</hi> white rocks to keepe out the inundations of our enemies.<note place="margin">Vt reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picularum i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> temporibus eſtiuis ſuaueo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes floſculos in prato deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans delicioſa condit m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lla ſuis colonis: Sic iſte prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps in Eccleſiae Anglicauae mel lificio ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras poenitiſſimè depaſcens, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berrima ſuis gaudia ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditat. <hi>Pſalm. 124 4 Reg. 9 Heſt. 1.5</hi>
               </note> In a word, this is the Phenix bird <hi>(de thure viuens)</hi> which may teach you all when to make your flight from ſinne. Let not your flight bee in winter, in the ſorrows of old age, and the ſorrowes of the gray head. It is a pleaſant ſong for young men to ſing in the ſpring time of their liues: <hi>Our ſoule is eſcaped as a bird out of the ſnare of the fowler.</hi> Who can but praiſe thoſe birds which liue in innocencie <hi>(grana comeden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes pura)</hi> and hate to do euill? Who can but ſmile at the proſpect of thoſe fields which yeeld plentifull increaſe to euery greene hearbe for the vſe of man, and will allow no roome to harmefull weedes? Loe heere <hi>Iaacob</hi> and <hi>Iaacob</hi> are thoſe birds, and thoſe fields; birds fethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and fields clothed with the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now compare all gardens with this field: the gardens of the Kings of Iudah and Iſrael, or of <hi>Haſhueroſh;</hi> all the delicate plots of the Aegyptian, Thebanes, Heſperines; the fields of Semiramis, Alcuines, or Spaniſh, or Italian gardens, of all the Romane deuices. Some of theſe were, either fantaſticall conceits and neuer were, or corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vanity and are not, or momentarie exiſtence and ſhall not be. But theſe two fields <hi>Iaacob</hi> and <hi>Iaacob</hi> with their gardener Chriſt Ieſus betwixt them, are euerlaſting fields: their Cedars, their high enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes; their hiſope, their lowly endeauours of grace ſhall neuer pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. Their leafe ſhall not fall, and beeing placed by the water ſide <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> ſhall bring forth his fruit in due ſeaſon,<note place="margin">Pſalm 1 Rom. 6.22</note> his fruit righteouſneſſe, and the end euerlaſting life. <hi>Behold, the ſmell of my ſonne is as the ſmell of a field.</hi> And heere I take my leaue of this field.</p>
            <p>Now let vs lie downe in peace: <hi>The field which the Lord hath bleſſed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pacem te poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus omnes.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I am at the laſt to ſpeake of bleſſing: this the fourth riuer that run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſoftly, <hi>in valle benedictionis,</hi> in the fall of Gods bleſſings. This the riuer of peace, which runneth ſoftly as the waters of Siloe: I could wiſh you all wel bathed in this water, and ſo commend you to the grace of our Engliſh Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould beginne this Treatiſe as <hi>Bonauenture</hi> for good ſpeede hath taught me,<note place="margin">Luk. 2 Ioh. 20 Prou. 3</note> I might commend the bleſſings of peace; that it is the language of heauen, the treaſure of Chriſt, and the faire path of God. By the vertue of peace the warfare betwixt God and man is well
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20345:27"/>ended, and betwixt man and man is well decided. Hee which knew how much the righteouſneſſe of God is in loue with peace, would with all his heart deſire peace, with this righteouſneſſe of God. This attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betwixt God and man, which our peace-maker hath made for <hi>Iaacob,</hi> is concluded in this bleſſed word <hi>bleſſed</hi> as a bleſſing of all bleſſings. The word is ambiguous in our Engliſh tongue, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be reſolued into his proprieties. Sometime bleſſing is the meanes to happineſſe, and ſometime happineſſe itſelfe. When it is the meanes, it is benediction, as it is heere; and when it is happineſſe, it is beatitude, as in other places. <hi>Beatitude eſt ſummus finis rationalis cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aturae tantum. Benedictio eſt aliarum creaturarum.</hi> The reaſonable creature onely can be bleſſed with beatitude;<note place="margin">Hine Diabolus eſt ſimia Dei et Papa Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boli.</note> the other creatures alſo with benediction; as the field, garden, cattell, basket and ſtore; or the day, as the ſabbath, or the iourney, as <hi>Iaacobs</hi> was. This is ſhort meaſure in reſpect of the other, for euery beatitude is a benediction, but they cannot be conuerted equally. One of theſe is more common then the other, as there are many motions to one end. The motions are more common then the end, for they either few or more may bee often hit, the end ſeldome, and neuer but at the laſt caſt. A man may attaine to ſome meanes, &amp; to no end, to ſome benediction, and to no beatitude, as they which runne and runne ſhort; or as the archer, which hauing the bleſſing of ſtrength, ſhooteth many arrowes at the marke, and all beſide. In ſome places you may finde him a bleſſed man whom the Lord hath inlarged with many gifts; as to increaſe and multiply in many children, riches, honours, dominions:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 144.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Happy are the people which are in ſuch a caſe, yea happie is the man which hath his quiuer full of them.</hi> This happineſſe is tranſlated beatitude, and yet is but temporary, extending to this preſent life onely. But this bleſſing is commonly called benediction,<note place="margin">Auſten. Beda. Thomas.</note> as the Fathers and Schoolmen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it. <hi>Benedictio Dei eſt donorum eius collatio, vel multiplicatio.</hi> In ſome places the bleſſed man is hee whom God hath enriched with eternall bleſſings: that hee is an happy man for the diſcharge of his debts, and the accompliſhment of his duties. The diſcharge:<note place="margin">Pſalme 32.1</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe iniquities are forgiuen.</hi> The accompliſhment:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 1.1.2.3</note> 
               <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the man that doth not walke in the counſell of the vngodly, but his delight is in the law of the Lord.</hi> This man thus diſcharged and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, is the bleſſed ſubiect into which <hi>beatus</hi> and <hi>benedictus</hi> are vnited into one. As in the name of <hi>Aſcher</hi> there is both bleſſing and happineſſe, benediction and beatitude,<note place="margin">Gen. 30.13</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Ah bleſſed am I for the daughters will bleſſe me, <hi>and ſhee called his name Aſcher,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20345:28"/>bleſſedneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. <hi>Ambroſ. Interliu.</hi> Gen. 49.20</note> Bleſſedneſſe indeed if we conſider the ſubſtance, for <hi>Aſcher</hi> was a figure of Chriſt, who enriched vs with his riches, that it is ſaid of him excellently: <hi>His bread ſhall be fat, and hee ſhall giue pleaſures for a King.</hi> To this purpoſe are heere diſcuſſed both an hiſtory and a myſtery.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyirl.</hi> Coloſ. 2.3 Matth. 13.46</note> In the hiſtory <hi>diuitiae mundi,</hi> in the myſterie <hi>deliciae Christi:</hi> who can be better vnderſtood in the full accompliſhment of all the Chriſt, in whom are hid all the treaſures? He is the Pearle of great prize, which ſaith of himſelfe: <hi>Riches and honour are with mee, euen durable riches and righteouſneſſe. Huius inopia ditat, fames ſatiat, mors viuificat.</hi> This is <hi>Aſcher, his bread ſhall be fat, and hee ſhall giue pleaſures for a King:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 25.6</note> 
               <hi>Ipſe eſt panis pinguis qui mentes fidelium impin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guat.</hi> In this Mountaine ſhall the Lord of Hoaſts make a feaſt of fat things, full of marrow and wines fined and purified to all his people. He giueth pleaſures vnto Kings <hi>paſcit thronos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyril.</note> 
               <hi>poteſtates, virtutes, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelos;</hi> who feedeth Patriarks, Kings, Prophets, and the Princes of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers.</p>
            <p>Thus may you perceiue bleſſing and bleſſedneſſe well met in him, who hath in himſelfe ſuch power of bleſſing, that he can make others bleſſed. This happineſſe is the high crowne of immortality, which wee all deſire to reach, as <hi>Heſter</hi> did the top of her husbands Scepter. The meanes whereby this bleſſing is inclined to vs,<note place="margin">Heſter.</note> and the ſtaires whereby wee climbe vp to it, are mercies and graces gifts of Gods bleſſing. In theſe the Lord beckneth to vs, to come to him as <hi>Ahaſhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eroſh</hi> held out the golden Scepter to the Queene: So <hi>Heſter</hi> drewe neere and touched the top of the Scepter. Many naturall men haue troubled themſelues in vaine, with many examinations of this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe to proue what it is. I may not ſtand here to rip vp the ſecrets of profound Philoſophers, from whoſe curious eies were hidden thoſe treaſures which they neuer found. Therefore they neuer had true peace:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 14.3</note> 
               <hi>for the way of peace haue they not knowne, they are all gone out of the way.</hi> Their higheſt point neereſt to our truth is this; that man hath no true bleſſedneſſe vntill hee be ioyned to the firſt of all things that can be vnderſtood. This is an high flight, and far beyond the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary thoughts of baſer mindes, yet far ſhort of the mount of true Diuinity. God is bleſſedneſſe it ſelfe, and to bee vnited vnto God is the perfect bleſſedneſſe of man in Ieſus Chriſt Emanuel, to knowe him, confeſſe him, and delight in him. But God is the obiect of mans faith, not the ſubiect of his intellect: the heart of man is too narrow a circumference to compaſſe God in his vnderſtanding. Therefore is Gods name incomparable, <hi>I am that I am,</hi> in the Preſent tence, whom
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20345:28"/>no power can ſhift out. Some haue tranſlated more properly, <hi>I will be, who I will be:</hi> to ſhew that God is able of himſelfe to hold his being and happineſſe againſt all rebellion, <hi>Stabiliſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> manet daens cuncta mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueri.</hi> To this purpoſe is that ſpoken of God; <hi>Dei eſſe eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gregory.</note> 
               <hi>diſſimiliter nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe;</hi> with God is no variablenes. Here then let vs acknowledge by faith, more then all thoſe deepe ſchollers could reach by reaſon that our bleſſedneſſe is in our vnion with God,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.7.</note> our peace which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>Among the ſecrets in the reueiled word, theſe two are great. One the hypoſtaticall vnion of two natures, that the <hi>word is made fleſh.</hi> The other is our ſpirituall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Niſi vna perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na eſſet Deus et homo, non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctè diceretur: Dominus gloriae crucifixus eſt.</note> our ſure copulation with Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out confuſion. That is a myſtery beyond naturall capacitie, only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by faith in the Church. This is alſo a great myſtery reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in ſhort patternes of the head and members knit, of the husband and wife vnited. In this exact and preſent worke, there are two bonds; one on Gods part; &amp; the other on ours. <hi>Ex parte Chriſti Sp. S. ex parte noſtra fides noſtra eſt vnionis vinculum.</hi> Thus by the twiſt of Gods holy ſpirit, and our hallowed faith, we are made one with Chriſt, and he is made vnto vs redemption, ſanctification, wiſdome and righteouſnes.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.29</note> Wherefore are theſe wonders come to paſſe but for our happineſſe, which cannot be had any where but in God the fountaine of bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. There doe wee daily tender vnto God that paiment of ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigntie which we may not yeeld to any other. God is ſufficient; ſo is none but he ſufficient of himſelfe, ſo is none but himſelfe ſufficient for himſelfe and for others; ſo is none other ſufficient for himſelfe and for all, and ſo are not all beſide him, put all together: This is our God: (Lord who is like vnto thee!) <hi>Qui ſedet in coelo repletiue;</hi> that heauen and earth are full of the maieſtie of his glory.<note place="margin">Pſal. 71.19 Epheſ. 1.23</note> This is our God (worſhip him all yee gods) who ſits aboue, and holdeth bleſſednes a faire marke in his hand, for vs all to runne vnto.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.</note> We muſt all runne; this life is the courſe; heauen is the goale. <hi>Expectat nos Deus pater vt haeredes, filius vt fratres, Sp. ſanctus vt vnctos:</hi> And here we are made a ſpectacle to the world, to Angels, and to men. Will you behold two runners, <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> both running after the Roe? Chriſt is the Roe which runs before them both in the race of happineſſe, like a Roe on the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of <hi>Bether.</hi> So did <hi>Iacob</hi> runne, and hath obtained by faith: ſo doth <hi>Iacob</hi> runne that he may obtaine by faith.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.21</note> Lord let him ſo runne that he may obtaine.</p>
            <p>O all yee vacant triflers of the world: why ſtand you heere idle as the men in the market place? What ſtand you for gazing one on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20345:29"/>as <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren. We muſt all labour in the vine yard, that we may receiue wages, all ſtriue that we may be crowned, all bee exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed that we may be in breath, <hi>non incipientibus ſed proficientibus.</hi> We muſt be I organimous, that we may continue to the end &amp; be bleſſed. Thus did the Apoſtle runne and continue to his ioy: I haue finiſhed my courſe: <hi>qui amat ardentius currit velocius:</hi> loue and great reward makes labour light, the reward is bleſſedneſſe.</p>
            <p>But it is high time to ſtep out of this digreſſion, from the marke to the meanes, from <hi>beatus</hi> to <hi>benedictus.</hi> There are apparant vnto vs in holy Scripture diuers bleſſings of diuers kindes. Some are of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour to the inferiour, ſome of the inferiour to the Superiour, and ſome of the equall to the equall. All theſe haue their ſpeciall diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and vſe. When the vnderling doth acknowledge the goodneſſe of the Superiour, and ſendeth vp to him thankes and praiſe for his kindneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103 1 Pſalm. 148</note> this ſeruice is called the bleſsing of reuerence. Thus the Prophet doth bleſſe God. <hi>My ſoule bleſſe thou the Lord.</hi> And ſuch a ſacrifice of praiſe is that in the melodious hymme of our praier book: <hi>O all yee workes of the Lord, bleſſe yee the Lord.</hi> The other bleſsing betwixt equals is termed <hi>benedictio charitatis,</hi> when one good chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an doth pray for an other, as Saint <hi>Peters</hi> counſell is <hi>bleſſe,</hi> and Saint <hi>Pauls, yea bleſſe I ſay and curſe not.</hi> But heere I may but touch and goe.</p>
            <p>The firſt bleſsing of the Superiour to the inferiour hath this branch alſo, as bleſsing of abſolute power, and bleſsing of authority, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more or leſſe. Bleſsing of abſolute power hath in himſelfe his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment aboue all bleſsings, as heauen which droppeth on the higheſt trees, hath his preheminence aboue all effuſions and drops of trees or mountaines. <hi>Euery good and perfect gift diſcendeth downe from aboue to the parts below;</hi> from heauen to earth, as the precious ointment went downe from the top of <hi>Aarons</hi> head to the beard,<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>33.2</note> &amp; the skirts of his clothing. This bleſsing of abſolute power is Gods onely to giue, who at his pleaſure can beſtow temporall or eternall gifts. Sometimes temporall, vpon the creatures for man, or vpon man in the vſe of the creatures.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.3</note> Sometimes eternall vpon the Saints, as he bleſſed the elect with all ſpirituall bleſsings in Chriſt, choſen before the foundations of the world.<note place="margin">Aquinas.</note> This bleſsing hath no match and therefore it is ſaid, <hi>bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicere Dei eſt cauſare bonitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> there is none but God which can cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate goodneſſe in man. The other Superiour bleſsing is by commiſsion to Gods Deputies, which bleſsing is either more-common, or more rare. The common bleſsing is praier, ſent as an Angell to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20345:29"/>fetch the bleſsing of God from the top of the ladder in heauen, to the foot of the ladder on earth. Thus the ſuperiours in the Church (for which cauſe we thinke ſuperiority expedient) do pray for the bleſsing of God inward and outward, and <hi>ex officio,</hi> doe ſhew that God will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow them wich are neceſſary. This bleſsing is dayly or ought to bee, of Kings to their ſubiects, Paſtors to their flocke, and Parents to their children. The bleſsing of the King to his ſubiects,<note place="margin">Ioſh 22 1 Paralip. 16 3 Reg. 8</note> as <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> bleſſed the <hi>Rubenites:</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> bleſſed the people in the name of the Lord; or as <hi>Salomon</hi> bleſſed all the congregation of Iſrael. Thus ſhall the King prolong his daies in the kingdome, and his ſonnes in the middeſt of Jſrael. The bleſsing of the Paſtor to the flock,<note place="margin">Deut. 17.20 Nomb 6.23 Leu. 9.23. Hebr. 7.1</note> ought to be as <hi>Aaron</hi> bleſſed the people at Gods appointment, as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the people when the glory of the Lord appeared, and as <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec</hi> bleſſed <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Prieſt of the moſt high God met <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham &amp;c.</hi> &amp; bleſſed him. This bleſsing when it is directed according to the preſcript and allowance of the word of God, is then of great power by the power of God annexed by promiſe. The bleſsing of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to their children is alſo of good vſe, and commendable among vs in England, for the good ſpeede commonly obſerued in theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings. <hi>Apud Britannos inprimis ſacra antiquitatis veſtigia etiamnum hodie clara in hac parte ſunt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hyperius. Rae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Britanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum clarita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſpecioſus.</note> The Britanes are moſt honourable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all Nations, for the continuance of this holy ordinance. This is without all doubt an holy order which the Lord ordeined from the beginning, that children might bee preſerued within the compaſſe of dutifull obedience to their parents, and might eſteeme greatly of their great office ouer them. Moreouer this obſeruation beeing a comely correſpondence to the fifth commandement, doth thereby approue it ſelf, that in our religion it ſhould not be neglected or reputed a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And this is more manifeſt by the reaſons of the Wiſe man, in which hee lappeth his counſels for the precious eſtimation of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents bleſſing.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>For the bleſſing of the father eſtabliſheth the houſe of the children, and the mothers curſe rooteth out the foundations.</hi> I might here lift vp ſome monuments, on which it hath been proued and writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, how the bleſsings &amp; curſes of parents haue kindled fire of heauen or hell, as if Gods will and the parents were all one. In this purpoſe an heathen ſpeaketh as if he had been a Diuine, in the skill of ſecrets: <hi>Si affirmabit pater aduerſus nos, pati nos oportet, quod ille faciat, cuius poteſtas plus poteſt.</hi> God doth iuſtly effect that which man doth iuſtly craue. But of all bleſsings by commiſsion, that is the higheſt, and of moſt power which is called the Patriarchall, or Propheticall bleſsing.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20345:30"/>With this bleſsing <hi>Iſaac</hi> bleſſed <hi>Iaacob</hi> and <hi>Iaacob</hi> after bleſſed his ſonnes. This is called a bleſsing of excellency, for that thoſe holy men indued with the ſpirit of Propheſie, did bleſſe with the bleſsing of God, which could not be ſupplanted. <hi>I haue bleſſed him and he ſhall be bleſſed.</hi> Theſe bleſsings were as delectable nuts in the Church; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in them beeing words of men, there was deliuered the bleſsing of God,<note place="margin">Cant. 6.10</note> as the kirnell in the nut: So that <hi>Iaacob</hi> gone towards his bleſsing might ſay, I went downe into the garden of nuts. The Lord had ſo enacted the couenant of grace with thoſe gracious fathers, that it did reſt in cuſtodie, <hi>vt ſanctum depoſitum,</hi> as an holy pledge de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered in truſt. They by their ſolemne bleſsing, might conuey this treaſure to their poſterities, in whoſe families the Church and life of ſaith was to continue till Chriſt his comming. Thus <hi>Noah</hi> bleſſed his ſonne <hi>Sem</hi> before, and <hi>Moſes</hi> bleſſed the twelue Tribes after. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Noah</hi> his bleſsing the queſtion is asked, wherefore that lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſe of Patriarchall bleſsing was beſtowed on <hi>Sem,</hi> when as <hi>Iaphets</hi> fauourable demeanour towards his father, was of equall reuerence and care for his fathers honour as <hi>Sems</hi> was. The anſwer to this queſtion is plaine; that the holy ghoſt did foreſee how from <hi>Sem</hi> ſhould ſpring <hi>Abraham,</hi> and all his holy followers, of whom the moſt bleſſed fruite that euer did grow was to come into the world. Therefore to <hi>Sem</hi> was that great Patriarchall bleſsing conueyed: yet had <hi>Noah</hi> an other bleſsing for <hi>Iaphet,</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> had for <hi>Iſmael,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> had for <hi>Eſau.</hi> This ſecondary bleſsing was far ſhort of the firſt, as the light of a ſtarre is ſhort of the light of the ſunne. Yet this bleſsing might be inlarged to <hi>Iaphet,</hi> if hee would light his ſtarre at the ſunne, and dwell within the light of the Church, within the tents of <hi>Sem,</hi> according to the condition of the bleſsing. <hi>God perſwade Iaphet that he may dwell in the tents of Sem.</hi> And thus is it happilie with vs Gentiles, conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and perſwaded to fetch our light at Chriſt, in the tents of <hi>Sem:</hi> our bleſsing is inlarged by him, and the Church with his bleſsing is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged by vs.</p>
            <p>Now then let me ſhew you how <hi>Iaacob</hi> the Hebrew and our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Iaacob</hi> are a bleſſed field. The ſuperiour bleſsing is vpon them both, and their bleſsing is made manifeſt vnto vs in three moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy allowances. The firſt is for ſcituation, the ſecond for plants, and the third for fruitfull vantages of watering. In the firſt <hi>Iaacob</hi> is a bleſſed field, ſcited in the ſunne, the faireſt funne the Sonne of God which alway ſhines. A bleſſed ſcite is <hi>Iaacobs</hi> conſcience, thus neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured with the ſun, his conſcience is aſweet lodging, ſweetned with
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20345:30"/>the ioies of Chriſt, as his father <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome. O bleſſed <hi>Iacob</hi> thy fathers bleſsing hath Iodged thee in the boſome of Chriſt, as the ſpouſe in the boſome of her husband.<note place="margin">Cant. 2.4</note> 
               <hi>Hee brought me into his wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller, and loue was his banner ouer me.</hi> God dwelling with <hi>Iaacob</hi> and <hi>Iaacob,</hi> is two waies. One in <hi>tabernaculo perſonali,</hi> in the fleſh of man, the other in <hi>tabernaculo miſtico,</hi> in the ſoule of man. Heere may you ſee the myſteries applied, which before we admired. In the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Chriſt his body is become bone of our bone; heere is our pleaſant ſcituation and our ſweete neighborhood. This lodging of Chriſt maketh all the faithfull ſmell ſweete, the maieſtie of his diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty beeing at reſt with our humanity in his holy incarnation. For this fauour <hi>Iaacob</hi> and <hi>Iaacob</hi> may either of them ſay:<note place="margin">Cant. 1.11 4 Reg. 20 Ioh. 11 4 Reg. 2.21</note> 
               <hi>Whileſt the King was at his reſt my Spicknard gaue the ſmell thereof.</hi> Heere <hi>Hezechias</hi> his ſicke body recouered, and <hi>Lazarus</hi> his dead body reuiued, that before, and this after, in the ſame power. Heere our bitter waters are made ſweet in our earthly current, that Chriſt may ſay to <hi>Iacob:</hi> I haue healed this water, death ſhall no more come thereof, nor barrenneſſe to the ground. Chriſt as a kinde phiſitian did vouchſafe to lodge in the ſicke mans bed, that by the touch of his body the poore patient might be healed. Thus the ſicke are cured as the diſeaſed woman was, by the touch of his garment when vertue went out of him.<note place="margin">Luke 8.46 4 Reg. 13.21 <hi>Eucherius.</hi>
               </note> And the dead are reſtored, as the corps recouered life by the touch of <hi>Eliſhaes</hi> bones. <hi>Excellens recuperatio per excellentiſſimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recuperatore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the faithfull. Man was much ſhaken, torne; and caſt downe in euerie ioint of his building, no mans merits could faſten againe one mans ioints: <hi>Chriſtus venit in carnem,</hi> God became man to repaire man, and to make vp all his breaches. In his incarnation hee came to <hi>Iacobs</hi> houſe as the holy viſiters into <hi>Abrahams</hi> tent, as a ſpecial friend which brought good prouiſion with him, all his ſtrength, skill, and goodneſſe, to doe for <hi>Iaccob</hi> all kinde of good. The ſecond dwelling which Chriſt hath with <hi>Iacob</hi> is in <hi>tabernaculo miſtico,</hi> by his word, ſacraments, graces, tokens of his loue, by his ſpirit the bond of vnity and comfortable ſeale of his ſure habitation: thus is <hi>Iaacob</hi> a bleſſed field. <hi>Behold, I am with you to the end of the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 28.20</note> 
               <hi>Deus accubuit in arca figuraliter, in Iacobo realiter:</hi> here is a reall and a royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,<note place="margin">Gratia Dei nos iuſtificans ineſt Deo, ſubiectiuè nobis obiectiuè.</note> the power and victory of the life and death of Chriſt is vpon all the borders of the Church. Heere is her pleaſant ſcituation, ſcited within the worthineſſe of her redeemer, within the court of honour of all his ineſtimable merits and mercies. The Churches gaines by this proximity with Chriſt, is the communication of all his participle
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20345:31"/>graces as courtiers gaine many gifts (not figures onely but actuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards) at the Kings hand by vicinity and neere attendance vnto him.<note place="margin">Sancti fide illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrati, gratiam in Deo intuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, vt oculi lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in ſole, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſque effecta in cordibus ſentiſcunt. <hi>Cant. 1.13</hi> Haimo. <hi>Pſalm. 51</hi>
               </note> A faithfull heart hath a ſingular delight to thinke how <hi>Iaacob</hi> may raiſe his glory and pleaſure in this royall preſence, as the ſpouſe doth. <hi>My beloued is as a cluſter of Camphire vnto me in the vines of Engad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di. Engaddi habet arbuſculas, liquorem balſami deſudantes,</hi> heere are the moſt holy drops of moſt precious Balme trickling into our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, to refreſh and eaſe them in their burning ſores. Here is our cleane heart and our right ſpirit; here we heare of ioy and gladneſſe that the bones which were broken may reioice. Heere wee haue our happy benedictions out of this circumfluent ſpring, our bleſſinge which are worthily decanted in Pſalmes, and ioyfully publiſhed in Anthemes of the giuer and receiuers. The giuer is God only, and the receiuers are Saints onely. God is the giuer only, <hi>a quo nil niſi bonum, vt a ſole nil niſi pulchrum,</hi> who onely giueth that only, which is good. The Saints are receiuers only, and none other haue any intereſt, or are capable.<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.36.</note> The Saints onely are free <hi>(if the Sonne haue made you free then are you free)</hi> none other haue any right in the liberties of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty. Thus much for the ſcituation of the Saints of Iſrael and England.</p>
            <p>The ſecond bleſſing of <hi>Iaacob</hi> and his brother, is in reſpect of plants, the moſt louely plants, the tree of knowledge and the tree of life, both planted in <hi>Iaacob. This is eternall life to know thee, &amp;c.</hi> Here is the beauty of Paradiſe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17 Ioh. 17.1.22</note> God in <hi>Iaacob,</hi> and <hi>Iaacob</hi> in God. <hi>The glory that thou gaueſt me I haue giuen them, that they may bee one as we are one:</hi> and thus <hi>Iaacob</hi> and all the Saints are one Paradiſe. Here the Lord made to grow euery tree pleaſant to the ſight and good for meat;<note place="margin">Geneſ 2</note> the tree of life and the tree of knowledge in the middeſt of the garden; Chriſt Ieſus in the heart of <hi>Iaacob</hi> in the middeſt of Paradiſe. This is the ancient ſtocke in whom all plants conſiſt, and from whom all the vigorous plants doe grow and ſpred in the Church;<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 1.17 2. Pet. 1.3 Rom. 8.32. Gal. 5.22 <hi>vt ſupra.</hi>
               </note> out of his godly power wee haue all things which pertaine vnto life and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Therefore might it well be ſaid, If ye haue Chriſt how ſhall ye not with him haue all things: <hi>Loue, Ioy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe, Goodneſſe, Faith, Meekeneſſe, Temperance.</hi> Theſe are plants which our heauenly father hath planted, daily increaſing with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of God in this garden,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudah.</hi> 1 Sam. 23.23</note> that a little one ſhall become a thouſand, all faire and ſtrong as the thouſands of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and the ſtrong men of <hi>Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third bleſſing of the field, is by the daily watering of the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20345:31"/>plants. All <hi>Iaacobs</hi> heauenly gifts, which hee hath receiued from the father of lights, are daily watered with ſhewers from heauen. Shewers from heauen of ſuch holy waters, which which our Sauiour watered his Diſciples.<note place="margin">Iohn 15.3</note> 
               <hi>Now are yee cleane through the word which I haue ſpoken vnto you.</hi> So long as we are claſped and barke bound in the vncleane ſcurfe of our corruption, we cannot proſper in religion; but in the waſhings of God we being cleanſed and purified, are more proſperous and louely before the Lord.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.11</note> Thus were the Corinthians bound in their ſinnefull pollutions, till they were clenſed and purified by the ſpirit of our God. And thus is Gods garden daily watered and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed againe with daily diſtillations of Chriſt his ſweat, ſweet ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the law for <hi>Iaacob:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 22.44</note> his ſweat like drops of bloud trickling downe to the ground. Downe to the ground, to the Church the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and ground of truth:<note place="margin">Pſal. 133 3</note> his ſweat did fall downe vpon it as the dewe of Hermon which falleth on the mountaines of Sion. The precious paſſion of our holy ranſome as a welcome cloud to refreſh and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our barren and drie ground, is daily melting vpon the Church, in daily praiers, ſermons, readings, and conferences. Thus is our field bleſſed: for there the Lord appointed the bleſſing to fall, and life for euer more It is eaſily perceiued whence all theſe waterings proceed, <hi>ab hortulano Chriſto:</hi> the good woman ſuppoſed Chriſt to be a gardener, and he is a gardener indeede more truly then ſhe ſuppoſed. This is the gardener which came by water and bloud to nouriſh his garden.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.6 1. Cor. 10.2</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> came by water, and ſo our fathers were baptized in the cloud and in the Sea. Chriſt came by water and bloud,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.5</note> yet without imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry difference of Baptiſme, for the fathers were baptized into the bloud of Chriſt. There is but one Baptiſme. They were all baptized into the bloud of the Lambe, which was ſlaine from the beginning of the world. The Apoſtle affirmeth of the Iſraelites,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.1 Act. 19.</note> that they were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed vnto <hi>Moſes:</hi> and the Diſciples at Epheſus anſwered for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that they were baptized vnto <hi>Iohns</hi> Baptiſme. And with right vnderſtanding we may readily diſcerne the vnitie of Baptiſme againſt all Idle ſuppoſitions: for <hi>Moſes, Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> were but Miniſters of one Baptiſme vnto the remiſſion of ſinnes in Ieſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.13.14</note> There was not any one baptized in any of their names (as it is argued that not any Corinthian was baptized in the name of <hi>Paul</hi>) that any ſhould beleeue in him, or worſhip him. It might well bee ſaid, that thoſe were baptized vnto <hi>Pauls</hi> Baptiſm, <hi>viz.</hi> in the doctrine of <hi>Paul,</hi> as the Iſraelites were in the doctrine of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and thoſe Diſciples in the doctrine of <hi>Iohn.</hi> And thus may you vnlooſe that knot, that the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20345:32"/>people beleeued the Lord and his ſeruant <hi>Moſes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14.31</note> that is they beleeued in God by the doctrine or miniſtery of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Now then let <hi>Iaacob</hi> and <hi>Iaacob</hi> confeſſe, that they haue all their waterings and waſhings of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Cant. 6.1</note> Moſt happy gardens thus watered and waſhed by this garde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Chriſt is come into his garden: in the middeſt of the garden is a fountaine of liuing waters,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4 Pſalm. 36.9</note> this maketh the garden bleſſed. Chriſt is the well of liuing waters: O bleſſed fountaine; with thee is the well of life: and this is the happineſſe of our Paradiſe, that both theſe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may ioyfully reioice with the Saints:<note place="margin">Gal. 2.20</note> thus <hi>I liue, yet not I now, but Chriſt Ieſus liueth in me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heere might I ſhew you <hi>triplicem Paradiſum,</hi> the terreſtriall, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, and celeſtiall paradiſe, all well met in Chriſt. The naturall man in the beauty of his princely I mage built vpright with his face prone to heauen, was our terren Paradiſe in Paradiſe before his fall. The ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall man renued and borne againe of water and of the ſpirit, in <hi>ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente fidei conſtitutus,</hi> ſet with his face towards the day ſpring; he is the beautifull continent of Gods manifold rich bleſſings to man; and this is our ſpirituall Paradiſe. The holy troops of Angels and Saints in heauen in their cheerefull recreations &amp; melodious pleaſures, are that heauenly Paradiſe,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12</note> of which S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth ſo triumph, albeit his ſight was but at a bluſh taken vp he knew not how. Here might I diſcourſe further of the earthly Paradiſe, how it is changed into a ſpirituall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe in the conuerſion of the ſinner, and how the ſpirituall Paradiſe is tranſlated by Ieſus Chriſt into the heauenly, one Paradiſe into an other. But the moſt exquiſite Paradiſe of all is Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>qui eſt triplex Paradiſus.</hi> Thinke of his body without ſpot, and of his ſpirit without ſtaine, and of his diuinity without mixtures of feble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and mutability, <hi>O triplex Paradiſus.</hi> Heere flouriſh (without thornes and thiſtles) all the faire flowers of Paradiſe. I would bee glad to ſtay heere, yet I muſt paſſe further from this faire contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with an obiectiue queſtion. What? is <hi>Iacob</hi> a field without weeds? No, ſuch a field is Chriſt; but neither <hi>Iaacob</hi> before, nor <hi>Iaacob</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor any other man but God.<note place="margin">Joh. 3</note> The enuious man is dayly ſowing his tares, yet there is a winde (which bloweth where it liſteth) daily ſent of God to kill thoſe ſeedes. Hee which well conſidereth this worke, may well thinke that <hi>Raphael</hi> the Angell of God is ſent of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to kill thoſe ſeedes in the quickning, to keepe <hi>Iaacob,</hi> and kill his enemies. The aduerſarie is daily breeding and feeding Giants, Atheiſme,<note place="margin">Gen. 14 12 <hi>Marlorat.</hi>
               </note> Gentiliſme, Mahumetiſme, and Papiſme, and theſe are the ringleaders of all violence againſt the Church, as the 4. Kings which
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20345:32"/>carried <hi>Lot</hi> away by force. Theſe marſhal their complices with ſtrong hand, and lead after them neglect and contempt of God, Pride, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Blaſphemie, Malice, Couetouſneſſe, Prodigality, Drunkenneſſe, &amp; ſuch an innumerous Army of Locuſts, that we haue cauſe to ſay as the Iſraelites ſaid, we haue ſeene monſters there. Happie is that man which taketh thoſe Giants whilſt they are young,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 137.</note> and daſheth their heads a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtones. Satan is alwaies hatching theſe Serpents, firie Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents in our boſomes; but Chriſt is the great Phyſitian,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3 Nomb. 21 <hi>Ferus.</hi>
               </note> lift vp as the braſen Serpent in the wilderneſſe, to kil thoſe Serpents and cure them which are bitten. So <hi>Moſes</hi> made a Serpent of braſſe: Chriſt is the Phyſitian, the Serpent without poyſon, as the braſen Serpent was. And as <hi>Moſes</hi> lift vp the Serpent in the wilderneſſe, ſo muſt the ſon of man be lift vp, that the wounded might bee healed, and the ſinner ſaued. Chriſt is the Angell of God, he is more then <hi>Raphael,</hi> both the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian and the phyſicke of God to heale our <hi>Iacob</hi> of all his hurts, that he may confeſſe of Chriſt as the other <hi>Iacob</hi> did:<note place="margin">Gen. 48.16</note> the Angell which hath deliuered me from all euill.</p>
            <p>Now then ſhall I offer a challenge in the name of this Angell, to all the enemies of <hi>Iacob?</hi> What Serpent, Dragon, Beare, Leopard, Fox, or Woolfe, Tyger, wild Boare, Lion, Giant, or Diuell himſelfe, can roote vp this field, thus kept vnder the ſhadow of the almighties wings.<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.5 <hi>Baſil.</hi>
               </note> This vineyard thus fenced with Gods bleſſings; election, vocation, rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, ſanctification, iuſtification, preſeruation, all ſure ſtakes, and all preparatiues to glorification, the crowne of all Gods bleſsings.</p>
            <p>Heere is a pleaſant Mount to ſtand on for the vpſhot of this text. The prouidence of God is as an high Zodiacke ouer Paradiſe, where the Lord is beholding in a pleaſant proſpect,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 11 1</hi> Multa ſine vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate Dei fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta ſunt, nulla ſine prouiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. <hi>Pſalm. 46 2.5 Pſalm. 76 6</hi> Corda diſponen do, caſus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutando, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſus ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, voluntates moderando, omnia intendo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ad finem mel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rem.</note> all the mirth-full bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of this field. This prouidence hath a long reach, <hi>tam ad ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miculos in coeno quàm ad angelos in coelo.</hi> It is <hi>Lorica caſtrorum,</hi> the fort of defence for all the tents in this militant Church: a ſure defence whither all celeſtiall birds do flie for ſafetie: fly to the mountaine as a bird. This prouidence did direct <hi>Iacob</hi> to his Patriarchall bleſſing, and maintained him in it. What though all the earth be mooued, and the mountaines fall into the Sea, yet ſhall our Paradiſe be ſafe, for God is in the midſt of it. What if all the world ſtand forth as <hi>Senacharibs</hi> hoaſt, againſt the Church, yet ſhall it ſtand vp: At thy rebuke O God of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> both the chariot &amp; the horſe are caſt aſleepe: here are they falne, but we are riſen and ſtand vpright. The Church of God is often repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to a ſhip, and the prouidence to a ſterne, which doth direct the Maſter &amp; his mate, the King &amp; the Prince, and all paſſengers in the ſhip
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20345:33"/>to their ſeuerall bleſſings, and guide them out of all their waiting dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. Thus are they brought into peace, externall, internall, eternall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a wealthy place, a quiet conſcience, all cloathed as the virgine in wrought gold, all ſmelling ſweet with Gods promiſes, and ſhining with the beautie of the Kings righteouſneſſe:<note place="margin">Pſalme. 37.6 Pſalm. 76.4</note> he ſhall bring forth thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe as the light, and thy iudgements as the noone day. Be the legions muſtered againſt <hi>Iacob</hi> as ſtrong as the hils of the robbers, or be they ſtout &amp; confident in themſelues,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1588. <hi>Mirabilis an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi> Pſalm. 37.20</note> as that Spaniſh Armado cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the inuincible Armado. Yet all their power ſhal vaniſh into ſmoak as that did. They all ouermatched with the prouidence of God, euen with the ſmoak did they conſume away:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 35.9.</hi> Faber quas ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit compedes, ipſe geſtat.</note> therefore King <hi>Dauid</hi> did ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace himſelfe in the meditation of this prouidence, reioiſing that God had ſo ſerued a defeſance vpon the plots of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> that his ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fell on his own head. And ſo all the fury of <hi>Pharaoh, Siſera,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> was retorted vpon themſelues,<note place="margin">Pape quid hoc eſt? Papam à Dauide noſtro interfectum, vt Goliah eſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prio ipſius gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio interemtus.</note> as the bookes &amp; libels of the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries are their owne ſnares, nailes on their owne heads, and ſwords in their owne ſides. Thus they periſhed at Endor in the well which they digged, and became dung for the earth. Heere then let vs all clap our hands with the ſonne of <hi>Amos,</hi> and ſay: If all people gather together on heapes and gird themſelues, they ſhal be broken, for God is with <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob.</hi> How fauourably did this prouidence guide the poore Chriſtians into Pella that little harbor (when they ſhould all haue beene eaten vp) that they might ſing vnto the Lord their high tower,<note place="margin">Vt Cadmaei fra tres ſeſe mutuo iugulantes: Ita Midianitae, Moabitae, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitae, et Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtae, hostes ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae mutuis ſeſe vulneribus confecerunt. <hi>Eſa 8.9</hi> Euſebius. <hi>2. Sam. 22.3.</hi> Eſpine. Vt coelum or bes in ſuo circuitu omnes comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitur, ita in Dei omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis amplexu, omnia circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur. Angl. Chron. redcunt Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia regna.</note> ſure refuge, and horne of their ſaluation? How happilie was that <hi>Carolus Martellus</hi> conducted out of al his hazards into the regencie of France, according to <hi>Salomons</hi> ſentence: for out of priſon he commeth forth to raigne, whenas he that is borne in his kingdome is made poore. What ſhould I ſpeake of that Hungarian great <hi>Matthius,</hi> how miraculouſlie he was preſerued and enthronized by this prouidence. I would willinglie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member many (if time could permit) as well as that famous young <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> who preuailed againſt thoſe coniured tirants, <hi>Diocleſian, Maximinian,</hi> &amp; others, and did win that peace to the Church which had no fellow. All thoſe preuailes were effected vnder this ſtanderd the prouidence of God. But once for all, with what an happy gale of wind was that repriſed Earle of Richmond (after 10. yeres baniſhment) conueyed hither, to aſcend vp to the throne of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth of England. O bleſſed prouidence which by ſpeciall fauor vnited <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac</hi> &amp; <hi>Rebecca</hi> for the leading of this bleſſed conſecration vnto <hi>Iacob.</hi> Which by a dexterous care for <hi>Iacob,</hi> hath vnited that <hi>Henrie</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth</hi> his wife, the white Roſe and the red, by whom this bleſſing is
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20345:33"/>arriued to our Land for vs all thus richly bleſſed.<note place="margin">The beauty and bands of <hi>Great Brittane</hi> Pſal. 18.11 Pſal. 68.17</note> Bleſſed with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of our incomparable King, our matchleſſe Prince, and all the King and Queenes royall progeny. A bleſſing brought vpon the wings of the wind, millions of hearty praiers: a bleſſing brought with Gods owne chariots the thouſands of Angels, that wee may all ſay and ſing, the Lord hath done great things for vs, whereof wee reioice. Theſe are the faireſt, ſweeteſt, moſt wholſome and welcome bleſſings, temporall bleſsings of our field. Therefore let vs all pray, that the father may be bleſſed more and more in his ſonne, and the ſonne euery day more in his father, that they may both liue for euer partners with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> coheires with Chriſt, and deare ſonnes to God our father, that of either of them hee may ſay for euer. <hi>Behold, the ſmell of my ſonne is as the ſmell of a field which the Lord hath bleſſed.</hi> To which bleſſed God, Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, one holy Vnity in Trinity, and Trinity in bleſſed Vnitie; let vs to our vttermoſt aſcribe all honor, and praiſe, and thanks, for euermore Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>The Booke to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſeeme to my ſelfe as a man decaied in his ſenſes, or if you will, as an houſe ſhaken in his building. I muſt confeſſe my copy was of dim ſight, &amp; my hand-writing of ill ſcribling, like rough timber, knotty, and vnready. Therefore though I be pained in my heart, for my manifold maimes, and looke in the eie of my Reader, like one which commeth out of the houſe with a ſcratched face, yet I hope to obtaine fauor of thee gentle Reader, with deſire to correct ſome</hi> errata, <hi>as followeth,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 1. Line 17. for flouds reade foulds. p. 2. l. 19. r. as lines are guided by their rule p. 4. l. 2. for attempteth, r. attexeth. p. 5. l. 28. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. ibid. in margin, r. <hi>vagien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem in cunis.</hi> ibid. <hi>adultam necare.</hi> p. 6. l. 11. for at once, r. one. p. 8. l. 33. for and now, r. Anſwere. No. p. 11. l. 32. for putteth, r. hideth. p. 14. l. 11. by their, r. either. p. 16. l. 5. r. <hi>coruus</hi> for <hi>conſonus.</hi> p. 18. l. 32. for oyle, r. oliue. p. 19. l. 2. r. <hi>and honour.</hi> ibid. l. 37. for <hi>teſtit</hi> r. <hi>deſit.</hi> ib. for with workes, r. which wanteth. p. 22. l. 11. for and, r. ah. ib. 28. 29. for haunt, r. heart. p. 24. l. 7. for are, r. our. p. 32. l. 16. r. all of Lebanon. p. 47. l. 14. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 48. l. 19. r. Alcinous.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
